<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A present for a papist, or, The life and death of Pope Joan plainly proving out of the printed copies and manuscripts of popish writers and others, that a woman called Joan was really Pope of Rome, and was there deliver'd of a bastard son in the open street, as she went in solemn procession / by a lover of truth, denying human infallibility.</title>
            <author>Cooke, Alexander, 1564-1632.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 183 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 86 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55699</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3244</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31913</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12273891</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12273891</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58390</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55699)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58390)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1512:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A present for a papist, or, The life and death of Pope Joan plainly proving out of the printed copies and manuscripts of popish writers and others, that a woman called Joan was really Pope of Rome, and was there deliver'd of a bastard son in the open street, as she went in solemn procession / by a lover of truth, denying human infallibility.</title>
                  <author>Cooke, Alexander, 1564-1632.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 165 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for T.D. ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Engraved illustrated frontispiece.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Cooke by NUC pre-1956 imprints.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Anti-Catholicism --  England.</term>
               <term>Papacy.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:58390:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A Woman Pope</hi> (as Hiſtory doth tell)</l>
                     <l>In <hi>High Proceſſion</hi> Shee in Labour fell,</l>
                     <l>And was <hi>Deliuer'd</hi> of a <hi>Baſtard Son;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thence <hi>Rome</hi> ſome call <hi>The Whore of Babylon.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <figDesc>depiction of the Whore of Babylon</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58390:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A Preſent for a Papiſt:</hi> OR THE LIFE and DEATH OF POPE JOAN Plainly Proving Out of the Printed Copies, and Manuſcripts of Popiſh Writers and others, that a Woman called JOAN, was really POPE of <hi>ROME;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And was there Deliver'd of a Baſtard Son in the open Street, as She went in Solemn Proceſſion.</p>
            <p>By a <hi>LOVER</hi> of <hi>TR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TH, <hi>Denying Human Infallibility.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>T.D.</hi> and are to be ſold at the Ship in St. <hi>Mary Axe,</hi> and by moſt Bookſellers, 1675.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:58390:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58390:2"/>
            <head>The PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THe Author of this following Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe is many years ſince deceaſed; a great Lover of <hi>Truth,</hi> and one who had been highly prefered in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> could he have diſpenſed with her <hi>Sons profitable Sin of lying and equivocation.</hi> In his time he was lookt upon as a man of a very acute Wit, a great <hi>Virtuoſe,</hi> yet of a meek and modeſt temper, one who valued <hi>Truth</hi> ſo much, and the <hi>World</hi> ſo little, that all that knew him, could do no leſs than approve and applaud his writings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they read them; and truly, as to the confirmation of his aſſertion, proving that there was a Woman called <hi>Joan,</hi> who was Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> he needed not the uſe of <hi>Lying,</hi> ſince he had ſo great a cloud of Witneſſes to manifeſt the Verity of the Story, and not a Proteſtant among them, but all eminent <hi>Pontificial Writers, (Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnacula
<pb facs="tcp:58390:3"/>Romanae Eccleſiae)</hi> whoſe <hi>Volumes</hi> he laboriouſly read over, and hath quoted them faithfully, in which quotations you will find none of the meaneſt of the Sons of the <hi>Romiſh Church</hi> have acknowledged, that there was a Woman Pope, and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral to this day, to their own ſhame and confuſion, muſt confeſs the truth of this Story.</p>
            <p>The Book was firſt publiſhed in the year 1602, Dialogue wiſe, between a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> and a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> wherein all the arguments that can be produced to prove the nullity of a Pope <hi>Joan,</hi> are fully and plainly anſwered; but the Book proving exceeding ſcarce; and the Reprinting thereof much deſired, I have taken the pains to alter the method only, but not the matter, and the only addition (in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner) is Pope <hi>Joans</hi> life tranſlated, as it is briefly deſcribed by <hi>B. Platina</hi> in his lives of the Popes; and indeed, all who have writ of her, have done it in ſo few words, that you muſt not expect the Tith of this <hi>Lady Errants Story</hi> in this ſmall Volume; not but that I am apt to believe that a
<pb facs="tcp:58390:3"/>
               <hi>Woman</hi> of ſuch eminent learning and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent parts, wherewith ſhe was endued, muſt perform many memorable actions in the World, beſides what were contein'd in her <hi>laſcivious Ramble</hi> with her <hi>luſty Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant</hi> to the City of <hi>Athens,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Rome,</hi> in which place ſhe behaved her ſelf in all reſpects, in maſculine apparel, like a learned and a Holy Man, till <hi>female frailty</hi> diſgraced her <hi>Papal Dignity</hi> with a <hi>Baſtard,</hi> of which ſhe was ſhamefully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered in the open ſtreet, as ſhe was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in <hi>Proceſſion,</hi> and both ignominiouſly died inſtantly thereon.</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Author</hi> hath given no very large account of her <hi>Life,</hi> ſuppoſing a full Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion would take up more Paper than lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Toſtatus</hi> his Works, who hath troubled the World with two ſheets for each day in his Life. But I conceive he writ this (as one wittily obſerves) to undeceive ſuch as took <hi>Rome for the model of the Heavenly Jeruſalem, and the Pope and Cardinals, for the Mayor and Aldermen of the Corporation.</hi> The proofs herein alledged for the Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of this Story, ſeem ſo apparently
<pb facs="tcp:58390:4"/>undeniable, that not only I, but many more of good credit, are clearly perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded there was ſuch a Woman. If mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters then have gone thus at <hi>Rome,</hi> (the people there having been moſt intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly abuſed, not only by this Female Pope, <hi>Donna Olympia,</hi> Siſter in Law and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruling Miſs to Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the Tenth, and others of the like <hi>Maſculine Gender</hi>) what hopes of <hi>Infallability?</hi> Let Children and Fools be pleaſed with Baubles, I hope the more rational ſort of men will not be impoſed on, and exempt the Pope from the determination in the Text, <hi>Every man i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> encompaſſed about with Infirmities.</hi> He that believes the contrary, to his peril let him do it, and to the obſtinate, who ſhall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt in this folly, I ſhall only ſay, <hi>Si Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulus vult decipi decipiatur.</hi> He that will be an Aſs may; I wiſh all good Chriſtians to have a care of being ſuch credulous Cocks-combs, and ſo</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58390:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Preſent for a Papiſt:</hi> OR THE LIFE and DEATH OF POPE <hi>JOAN, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>JOhn Engliſh</hi> or Pope <hi>Joan,</hi> as you may read in <hi>Platina</hi>'s Lives of the Popes, was born at a place called <hi>Mentz</hi> in <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> who concealing her Sex in a Maſculine habit, being a young Woman, travel'd with a man of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Learning to <hi>Athens,</hi> whom ſhe infinitely loved for the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of his parts, having ſufficient ingenuity to qualify her for a judge in that particular. Such was her deſire of knowledge, that for ſome
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:58390:5"/>time ſhe wholly baniſh'd her thoughts from every thing that had the leaſt appearance of what was ſenſual, and applying her ſelf ſolely to her ſtudy, in a little time ſhe ſo improved her ſelf in all Arts and Sciences, by conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing with the Learned of thoſe times, with the aſſiſtance of her no leſs Learned Companion, that in Philoſophy ſhe had few E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quals, and a while after coming to <hi>Rome,</hi> in Theology ſhe had as few Superiours. By her indefatigable reading and acute diſputing, ſhe ſoon obtain'd ſo much good will and Credit amongſt all ſorts of Perſons, that ſhe was not only cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up for a great Wit, but a man of unimitable holyneſs and piety, and this vogue ran ſo uncontrou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lably general among the wiſer ſort, that <hi>Leo</hi> the Fourth deceaſing, by the conſent of all, as <hi>Martinus</hi> ſaith, ſhe was choſen Pope. Being hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:58390:5"/>warm in her Papal Seat, her Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety gave place to her Leachery, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch, that admitting either her learned Fellow-traveller, or one of her Menialls, as ſome imagin, into her looſe embraces, ſhe conceived with Child, and as ſhe grew bigger and bigger, every day produced new inventions to conceal her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnation, ſo ſuptly contrived, that this growing infamy was known to none but him that was the cauſe thereof: but miſchief on't, not dreaming that her time approacht ſo near, as ſhe was going from the <hi>Vatican</hi> to St. <hi>John Laterans</hi> in Proceſſion, between <hi>Nero</hi>'s Coloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and St. <hi>Clements,</hi> ſhe fell in Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, and was Delivered of a Son, and dyed in that very Place, having ſate as Pope two years one month and four days, and was buried with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt honour and ſolemnity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jacobus Bergomenſis</hi> differs little in opinion from the aforeſaid rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58390:6"/>a Man whom <hi>Trithemius (Lib. de Eccleſiaſticis Scriptoribus)</hi> applauds for being well read in Scripture, a famous Hiſtoriogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher, and one that was witty, elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, and of a good life and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, and therefore we may dare credit ſuch a Perſon, who ſays,<note n="a" place="margin">Supplement Chron. lib. <hi>11.</hi> ad Anno <hi>858.</hi> Impreſ. Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiis. An. <hi>1486.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Johannes Septimus Papa, natione Anglicus poſt Leonem Pontiſicem, Pontifex factus ſedit, An.</hi> 2. <hi>Menſ.</hi> 5. <hi>Hunc tradunt fuiſſe faeminam,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>John</hi> the VII. by Country <hi>Engliſh,</hi> was created Pope after, next after <hi>Leo,</hi> and ſate two years five Months; they ſay this was a Woman, and that ſhe went very young out of <hi>England</hi> to <hi>Athens</hi> with a learned man that was in Love with her, and that thereby, hearing good Profeſſors, ſhe profitted ſo much, that coming to <hi>Rome,</hi> ſhe had few like her in Divinity. Whereupon by her Reading, Diſputing, Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Praying, ſhe got her ſelf
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:58390:6"/>ſo much favour, that upon <hi>Leo</hi> his death, ſhe was Choſen Pope in his Room, (as many men ſay by common conſent; but ſee the luck of it, a while after, ſhe was got with Child by one of her acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and was delivered thereof in the time of her Papacy; for going from the <hi>Vatican</hi> to St. <hi>John Laterans</hi> in Proceſſion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Coloſſes</hi> and St. <hi>Clements,</hi> e're ſhe was aware, Child-birth Pangs ſeized her e're ſhe was aware, and was delivered in the High-ſtreet without the help of any Midwife, but ſhe dyed preſently, and was buryed without the leaſt ſolemnity in the ſame place, with her Bantling lying by her. Now in deteſtation of ſo foul a fact, and for the continuing the memory of ſo lude an action, the Popes to this day, when they go in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, to ſhew their diſlike to the place of her Travel, which was in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58390:7"/>the midſt of her way, forſaking it, do turn into by-lanes, and by-ſtreets, till they have left that on their backs, and then returning into the ſame ſtreet again, they go forward with their Proceſſion. And for avoiding the like miſchief for the future, it was decreed: that none ſhould be conſecrated Pope, before the youngeſt Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Deacon had tried by touching, (whilſt the Perſon to be conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated ſate on a Cloſe-ſtool) that he was a man.</p>
            <p>I am not ignorant how incredu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous this ſtory appeares to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts, and how fabulous and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous ſome have endeavour'd to render it by their ſophiſtry and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery, which ſhameful practices we need not wonder at, if we conſider how cuſtomary it is for them to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vow manifeſt untruths, and deny known truths, eſpecially if they produce any advantage to the vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58390:7"/>of their Popiſh perſwaſion; all which is as eaſy to prove, as to object againſt them; which though it may be demonſtrated by diverſe particulars, <hi>viz.</hi> By Parſons and Biſhops, denying that they call the Pope their Lord God: by <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mins</hi> denying that any Jeſuit had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hand in the Gunpowder Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: by their general denying that Pope <hi>Honorius</hi> the firſt was an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritick, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet moſt apparently their impudence appeares, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying the report of a <hi>Joan</hi> that was a <hi>quondam</hi> Pope of <hi>Rome;</hi> which I ſhall endeavour to prove by a Cloud of witneſſes, not any of our own Brethren, but the ſons of the Romiſh Church, which purpoſely I have done for the greater confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of my arguments; for as <hi>Novatian</hi> ſays, <hi>de Trinitate firmum eſt genus probationis quod etiam ab Adverſario ſumiter, ut veritas eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ab inimicis veritatis probetur;</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:58390:8"/>that is a ſtrong proof which is wrung out of the adverſary, when the enemies of truth are driven to bare witneſs unto the truth. And as<note n="b" place="margin">Vives de Inſtrument. probabilita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</note> another, <hi>Amici contra amicum et inimici pro inimico invincibile teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monium eſt.</hi> Which ſounds thus as I conceive; the teſtimony of a Papiſt againſt a Papiſt, and the teſtimony of a Papiſt for a Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, is without exception. If I have given an impartial and true account of this <hi>Joan,</hi> the Woman Pope, manifeſtly proving there was ſuch a Perſon who ſate in the Papacy, and dyed therein with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy, againſt the ſurmiſes and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections made to the contrary, by <hi>Robert Bellarmin</hi> and <hi>Caeſer Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> Cardinals, <hi>Onuphrius Harding, Saunders, Cope, Genebrard, Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nartius, Florimondus, Papirius, Maſo, Parſons, &amp;c.</hi> I would then have the Romaniſt lay aſide all prejudice, and bare Witneſs
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:58390:8"/>with me, if he can bring more ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid arguments to the contrary, I am ready to be convinced, being content to learn of him if he can better inform my judgment, as<note n="c" place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract. cap. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> St. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> did of <hi>Tychonius</hi> the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retick. To conclude my <hi>proaemium</hi> with all ſincerity, I profeſs, that though it may be gather'd out of <hi>Campian</hi> a Tiburn-martyr, and the Papiſts Champion, that they believe one Heaven cannot hold them and Proteſtants; though<note n="d" place="margin">Fieri nequit ut <hi>Luthera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Jehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam,</hi> evadat, ex externis ignibus eripi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atur. Si men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tior damner ipſe cum <hi>Luci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fero,</hi> ſaith <hi>Coſterus,</hi> Reſp. ad Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futat. Lucae <hi>Oſiandri</hi> Propoſit. <hi>8.</hi> pag. ult.</note> 
               <hi>Coſteras</hi> wiſh ſtrangly that he may be damn'd with the Devil to all Eternity if any of us be ſaved; yet their uncharitableneſs and cruelty towards us from time to time ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended cauſeleſly ſhall work no ſuch effect in me, but on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, I wiſh them well, and ſhall conſtantly pray for the welfare of their Souls; that they may have eyes to ſee the truth, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuity to acknowledge it.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:58390:9"/>
            <p>Give me leave now to come to the Proof of this famous Hiſtory of Pope <hi>Joan,</hi> and by the way, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks I hear ſome opinionative ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate Romaniſt ſay that the whole ſtory of Pope <hi>Joan</hi> is a fond, vain, and meer fable, a ridiculous ficti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſo known to the more learned ſort of Proteſtants among you, but that you will not leave deluding the world with it for want of other matter; beſides, there are ſo many improbabilities and moral impoſſibilities in this Tale; as no man of any mean judgment, diſcretion, or common ſenſe will give credit thereto; but will ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily ſee the vanity thereof. In a word, I ſay<note n="e" place="margin">Impudentiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimè ficta, ſtultiſſimè credita. <hi>Fernartius</hi> de utilitate legendae hiſt. lib. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>105.</hi>
               </note> he was a Knave that invented it, and he is a Fool that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth it, eſpetially if he compares it with what is written on the ſame ſubject by <hi>Buchingerus</hi> in <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni,</hi> by <hi>Charanza</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> by <hi>Onu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrius, Bellarmin,</hi> and <hi>Baronius</hi> in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58390:9"/>
               <hi>Italy,</hi> by <hi>Tarianus,</hi> and <hi>Bernartius</hi> in <hi>Belgia,</hi> by <hi>Pontacus</hi> in <hi>Aquitania,</hi> by <hi>Genebrard</hi> and <hi>Papyrius, Maſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> by <hi>Saunders, Cope, Harding,</hi> Father <hi>Parſons,</hi> and others which were <hi>Engliſh</hi> men.</p>
            <p>To all thoſe particulars, and what elſe hath been objected, to prove the nullity of this Hiſtory, I ſhall endeavour to anſwer and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute as mildly as the ſubject will permit, and firſt, did it not paſs for currant, <hi>ſans contradiction,</hi> till with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſomewhat more than a Century of years, <hi>viz.</hi> Till the year 1566. That <hi>Onuphrius</hi> the Fryer began to boggle at it; he was the firſt that ever by reaſon indeavour'd to diſcredit the report of it, and yet confeſſeth that many worthy men as well as vulgar, believed it for a truth: <hi>Multos &amp; magni nominis vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ros hiſtoriam hanc ſuſcipere eam quoque vulgo verum exiſtimary.</hi> Beſides, it is to be found in <hi>Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58390:10"/>Scotus,</hi> in <hi>Sigibert,</hi> in <hi>Gote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fridus Viterbienſis,</hi> in <hi>Johannes de Pariſiis,</hi> in <hi>Martinus Polonius,</hi> in <hi>Petrach,</hi> in <hi>Boccace,</hi> in <hi>Ramulſius Ceſtrenſis,</hi> in <hi>Johannes Lucidus,</hi> in <hi>Alphonſus e Carthagena,</hi> in <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricus de Niem,</hi> in <hi>Chalcocondilas,</hi> in <hi>Platina,</hi> in <hi>Palmerius,</hi> in <hi>Naucle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> in <hi>Sabellicus,</hi> in <hi>Trithemius,</hi> in <hi>Voleteranus,</hi> in <hi>Bergomenſis,</hi> in <hi>Schedel,</hi> in <hi>Laziardus,</hi> in <hi>Fulgoſus,</hi> in <hi>Textor,</hi> in <hi>Gaſſarus,</hi> in <hi>Mantuan,</hi> in <hi>Crantius,</hi> in <hi>Caranza,</hi> with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more of the Papiſh faction; ſome <hi>Grecians,</hi> ſome <hi>Italians, Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards, French, Germans, Polo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, Scots, Engliſh,</hi> and yet not one of them a <hi>Lutheran.</hi> If theſe Authors added no weight to the verity of this Hiſtory, yet me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks her Image might, which is ſet up among the reſt of the Images of the Popes in the famous Church of <hi>Siena</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> and is to be ſeen there at this day; which the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58390:10"/>of that place would not ſuffer to be defaced at the laſt repairing of that Church, though the Jeſuits did urge him much to do it. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, was there not made of old for fear of ſuch like cheats and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes a ſtool of eaſement, on which Popes were ſet at their inaugurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for proof of their humanity? was their not a Marble Image fet up as a Monument thereof, in the place where ſhe Miſcarried, <hi>viz.</hi> In one of the chiefeſt ſtreets in <hi>Rome,</hi> which Monument was likewiſe to be ſeen within this few yeares, no longer ago than in the time of <hi>Pius</hi> the fifth. Laſtly, is it not written by men of their own perſwaſion, that all Popes when they go in Proceſſion, refuſe to go through that ſtreet in deteſtation of that fact, but go further about. To this the Romaniſts do anſwer, it is not ſo much in deteſtation of any ſuch ſuppoſed fact that they
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58390:11"/>leave the ſtraight and nearer way to the <hi>Lateran Church,</hi> but becauſe that ſtreet is <hi>Auguſta &amp; anfractuoſa,</hi> a narrow winding ſtreet, and in that reſpect unfit for ſo great a Train as ordinary accompanies the Pope to paſs orderly through, as <hi>Onuphrius, Bellarmin,</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mondus</hi> have obſerved. But if it be true what <hi>Philippus Bergomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis</hi> hath regiſtred, this obſervation is falſe,<note n="f" place="margin">In Supple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Chron. ad Annum <hi>158.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>eo omiſſo</hi> (ſaith he) ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Popes turning out of that place of the ſtreet wherein Madam <hi>Joan</hi> was deliver'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the benefit of a warm Bed, Midwife, Nurſe, or Caudles to comfort her, <hi>Declinat ad diverticu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la vicoſque, et ſic loco deteſtabili po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtergato reintrantes, iter perficiunt quod caeperunt:</hi> that is, leaving the way, they turn into by-lanes and by-ſtreets, and as ſoon as they are beyond that deteſtable place, they turn into their way again, and ſo
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:58390:11"/>go on to the perfecting their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion. Now, if upon their leav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that ſtreet, they enter into by-lanes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And having paſt that ominous place, they turn in again; the reaſon why they leave that ſtreet cannot be becauſe it is nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and winding in and out, for doubtleſs thoſe by-lanes are as nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. And by their turning out and returning into the ſame way a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, they wind as often in and out as if they went along through the ſame ſtreet, though it were very crooked. In confirmation where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of<note n="g" place="margin">De vitis Pontif. in vita <hi>Johan. 8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Platina,</hi> who knew <hi>Rome</hi> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry well, and was deſirous enough to cover the Popes nakedneſs here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, as much as he could with any honeſty, confeſſeth that this is probable enough.</p>
            <p>As to the Marble Image erected <hi>in perpetuam rei memoriam</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Lib. de pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilegiis &amp; juribus Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perii.</note> 
               <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odoricus de Niem,</hi> who was former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Secretary to a Pope, ſays <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huc
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:58390:12"/>vetus Statua marmorea illic po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſita figurative monſtrat hoc factum,</hi> unto this day an old marble Image errected in that place, ſheweth the matter under a figure. Now obſerve what a ſlender evaſion the Romaniſts make uſe of, in acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging there was ſuch a Statue but reſembled not in the leaſt a Woman lying In, nor was the Boy engraved by her like a Child in Swadling-Clouts, but like one of ſome years.</p>
            <p>This exception is to little pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, for that age was an ignorant, illiterate, witleſs age, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore perhaps had no more Skill in Graving, Carving, and Painting, then they had, whom <hi>Aelian</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, who were forced to write over or under their Pictures, <hi>Hic eſt Bos; ille Equus; haec Arbor;</hi> this is a Bull, this an Horſe, and this a Tree; that men might know what creature it was they Paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58390:12"/>
               <hi>Aeneas Sylvius</hi> pointing to a more ingenious time than that of <hi>Pope Joan,</hi> condemns the Painters and Carvers thereof for notorious bungling Botchers, ſaying thus, <hi>If we could take a vew of grav'd or paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Images made two or three hundred years ago, you would find them pourtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not like men, but Monſters and hob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gobblins;</hi> ſuch an artiſt probably had the handling of Pope <hi>Joans</hi> ſtatue; however as ill framed as it was, <hi>Pius Quintus</hi> thought it as it ſtood, that it diſcovered more than he willingly would have known, and therefore removed it and caſt it into the <hi>River Tyber,</hi> not becauſe it diſgraced the ſtreet, but, <hi>ut memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam illius aboleret,</hi> that he might extinguiſh the memory of that ſhameful action, and this is not onely witneſſed by Travellers, that were in <hi>Rome,</hi> but by <hi>Elias</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Hiſt. a Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuitici Ordinis cap. <hi>10.</hi> de Jeſuitarum Patre &amp; Matre.</note> 
               <hi>Haſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenmuller</hi> formerly a member of the fiery order of <hi>Jeſuits.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:58390:13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Bellarmin in lib. de Rom. Pontif.</hi> will not allow of this <hi>Stool of Eaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> for ſays he, of a ſtool of eaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to try the Popes Sex, there is no where any mention; <hi>Onu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrius</hi> averring that it is but a meer toy, and an idle conceit of idle people; yet <hi>Philippus Bergomenſis,</hi> a man of great learning and eſteem in his time, (as <hi>Trithemius</hi> atteſts) records it as an undeniable truth, that there was ſuch a thing; for upon mention made of Pope <hi>Joans</hi> ſtory, <hi>Ad evitandos ſimiles errores ſtatutum fuit (ſaith he) ne quis de caetero in B. Petri collocaretur ſede priuſquam per perforatam ſedem fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turi Pontificis genitalia ab ultimo Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acono Cardinale attractarentur:</hi> for avoiding like errour for the future it was decreed that no man ſhould be held for Pope, till the youngeſt Cardinal Deacon had found by tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, while he ſate upon a ſtoole of eaſment, that he was a man;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:58390:13"/>which is likewiſe teſtified by<note n="k" place="margin">De rebus Turcicis lib. <hi>6.</hi> pag. <hi>98.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onicus Chalcho condilas;</hi> for upon relation of that ſtory he thus pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds, <hi>Qua propter ne decipiantur i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terum ſed rem cognoſcant neque am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bigent Pontificis creati virilia tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunt &amp; qui tangit acclamat: Mas nobis Dominus eſt:</hi> that is, leaſt they ſhould be deceived again, they make proof of the Popes man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood by feeling, and he that feel-makes it known by crying our Lord and Maſter is a Man. And <hi>Sabelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> writing the ſame matter, ſays, <hi>There is to be ſeen at this day in the Popes Pallace a Marble Chair where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the new Pope preſently upon his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection is ſet down, that as he ſits, the loweſt Deacon may make trial of his humanity by touching or feeling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As much may be read in <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Brewin,</hi> who lived in the year 1470. for in <hi>Capella Salvatoris</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>In the Chappel of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, there are two or more Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Chairs with holes in them, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:58390:14"/>in (as I heard) there they make proof whether the</hi> Pope <hi>be a man or no.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Romaniſts confeſs there is ſuch a Chair, but never intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the uſe afore recited; for (ſay they) he ſits not therein in a corner, but in the great Church of St. <hi>John Lateran,</hi> where a vaſt concourſe of People come to ſee him; where he is attended by the whole Colledge of Cardinalls, with many Embaſſadours of Kings and Princes; whereas a cloſer place was fitter for that Purpoſe, and they might more convenient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have made tryal of his humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the conclave, wherein he was choſen, and ſo they did it ſeemes; for preſently upon their electing of him, before they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamed him <hi>Pope,</hi> they ſate him in a Chair in their Conclave, as you may read <hi>in the book of holy Ceremonies,</hi> dedicated to <hi>Leo the tenth,</hi> whereby you may ſee how
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:58390:14"/>idly<note n="m" place="margin">Lib. <hi>3.</hi> de Rom. Pont. cap. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bellarmin,</hi> talks (if I may be ſo bold to ſpeak ſo of ſo great a Cardinal) who taking upon him to clear the Point, never ſpeaks of his ſitting in the chair in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clave, but only of his ſiting in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chairs at St. <hi>John Laterans,</hi> as though he had been chaired only Publickly, and not in private, and that he himſelf had ſaid ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Point in queſtion, by proving, that in Publick there was no ſuch concluſion tryed with the <hi>Pope;</hi> whereas the concluſion was tryed in ſecret. Now, ſhould you ask the queſtion of any of them to what end does he ſet in ſuch a Chair in Publick, I warrant you the reply will be, <hi>that thereby he may be put in mind, that he is not God but Man: in as much as he ſtands in need of a Cloſe-ſtool as well as others;</hi> ſo ſays <hi>Florimondus:</hi> and indeed I think he hath need to be put in mind thereof. For
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:58390:15"/>though ſome Papiſts deny it ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully,<note n="n" place="margin">N. D. in his Warnword to Sir. <hi>Fr. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtings</hi> encoun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, cap. <hi>2.</hi> fol. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> yet there have been popiſh Paraſits, who have in plain terms called the <hi>Pope</hi> (as <hi>St. Thomas</hi> term<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Chriſt, Joh.</hi> 20.28.) their Lord, and God; and there are ſtill ſuch, who give him ſuch titles as are due to God alone, and rob God of ſome part of his power, to beſtow it on him. See <hi>Stapleton princip. fid. doctrin praefect. ad Greg.</hi> 13. <hi>Plane ſupremum in terris numen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But methinks they ſhould not need to have ſet him in ſuch a Chair, to ſuch a purpoſe, for his own neceſſity would have compeld him to ſet himſelf thereon ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily every day; and his Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pot would have ſerved to put him in mind of his humanity ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: thus <hi>Autigonus</hi> the elder (as<note n="o" place="margin">Part. <hi>2.</hi> Moral. lib. de Iſide &amp; Oſiride.</note> 
               <hi>Plutarch</hi> relates) was convinced that he was a Man and not a God. Beſides, methinks they ſhould not have intended ſuch a Myſtery by
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:58390:15"/>ſuch a Ceremony, becauſe they ſet him therein before he was in his <hi>Pontificalibus:</hi> for till he be Mitred, till he be Crowned, till he have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the Keys, whereby is deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his power to bind and looſe; and a Rod whereby is ſignified his power to puniſh; I ſay I ſhould think there ſhould be no fear of forgetting himſelf. Again, had it not been better think you, if they had aimed at any ſuch marke, to have cauſed a <hi>Boy</hi> to come every morning unto the <hi>Popes</hi> Chamber door (after the example of <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>Macedon</hi>) who ſhould have whoopt him out of his bed, and bid him remember that he was mortal.</p>
            <p>And now ſee how induſtrious the Romaniſts are, by endeavouring to obliterate, or remove what ever may aſſiſt the continuance of the memory of this <hi>Pope Joan;</hi> for as <hi>Pius Quintus</hi> threw into <hi>Tyber</hi> her
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:58390:16"/>marble Image which ſtood in the ſtreet where ſhe was deliver'd, ſo by <hi>Clement the eight,</hi> by the perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Cardinal Baronius,</hi> her Image in the Church of <hi>Siena</hi> is defaced; now if the preſent <hi>Pope</hi> will but burne all the books too, which are writ of <hi>Pope Joan,</hi> all evidences then would be totally loſt, it would be eaſily for them then to prove that there never was ſuch a <hi>Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial Woman.</hi> I but (ſays the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt) what if her Image had ſtood ſtill, is there any ſence, that becauſe of ſuch a portraiture we are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bound to believe there was ſuch a <hi>Pope;</hi> if we believe Paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and Carvers we ſhould make find work indeed; and ſo we ſhall indeed if we believe their Painters, and Carvers. For we find the <hi>Trinity</hi> painted by them in the likeneſs of a Man with three faces: ſometimes like a Man with two heads having a <hi>Dove</hi> between them;
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:58390:16"/>both which faſhions of painting the <hi>Trinity</hi> is monſtrous in<note n="p" place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> de Imag. cap. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bellarmins</hi> opinion. We find our Saviour Chriſt painted with long hair, as though he had been a Nazarite by vow, which conceit is controuled by<note n="q" place="margin">For <hi>Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites</hi> muſt drink no Wine <hi>Numb. 6.3.</hi> yet our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our did, <hi>Mat. 11.19.</hi> and <hi>26, 29.</hi>
               </note> Holy writ. We find him ſet on a Weather-cock on the top of the <hi>Temple of Jeruſalem,</hi> as though the <hi>Temple</hi> had aſpire-ſteeple like ours, which is falſe. We find the <hi>Virgin Mary</hi> treading on the <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents</hi> head, which the <hi>Scriptures</hi> foretold <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf ſhould do. We find her richly apparel'd in a Gown of wrought gold, whereas, queſtionleſs her habit was very mean and ordinary; and with a pair of beads in her hand; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as a thouſand years after <hi>Chriſt,</hi> beads were not uſed throughout the world. Beſides, their Painters recommend unto us a <hi>Saint on horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back,</hi> whom they call <hi>George,</hi> and another on foot, as big as a Giant,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:58390:17"/>whom they call <hi>Chriſtopher,</hi> and a <hi>She-Saint</hi> broken on the wheel, whom they call <hi>Catharine,</hi> and a fourth drawn in peices by horſes, nick-nam'd <hi>Hippolitus:</hi> whereas in all antiquity there is no mention made of any ſuch <hi>Saints.</hi> Thus you ſee we have no reaſon barely to believe painting and carving, but if Book-proof, or Tradition con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur with them, we may give ſome credit to them.<note n="p" place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> de Rom. Pont. cap. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bellarmin</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf is of the opinion, <hi>that there can be no error in ſubſtance, as long as (beſides book-proof) there are Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Stone or of Braſs for the proof of any antient report:</hi> thus if he ſpeak the words of truth the truth is with us; for, beſides Monuments of Stone, we have the Teſtimonies of many authentick Writers: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt whom, <hi>Charanza a</hi> Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard, who, <hi>Florimondus</hi> ſays, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved the ſtory of <hi>Pope Joan</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he undertook the task himſelf;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:58390:17"/>but he belies him; for theſe are his words,<note n="t" place="margin">In Sum. Conc. p. <hi>370.</hi> Edit. Paris, <hi>1564.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Johannes</hi> 8. <hi>Papa</hi> 105. <hi>ſub Petro ſedit An.</hi> 2 <hi>Mens. Dies</hi> 4. <hi>de hoc ferunt, quod malis artibus Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificatum adeptus eſt, quoniam cum eſſet faemina, ſexum mentitus eſt; et poſtea à ſervo compreſſa, doloribus circumventa, mortua eſt:</hi> in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh thus; <hi>John the eight Pope.</hi> 105. <hi>Pope from St. Peter, ſate</hi> 2 <hi>years</hi> 1 <hi>month</hi> 4 <hi>days. They report of this Perſon that he got the Papacy by evil means, becauſe he feined himſelf to be a man, whereas in truth he was a Woman, who being afterwards begot with child by one of her ſervants, fell in travel and dyed therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>z. Krantius,</hi> who is recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended by <hi>Pontanus</hi> for a famous Hiſtoriographer, and one that writ before <hi>Luthers</hi> times, and is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the leſs to be ſuſpected for partiallity, ſays thus, <hi>Johannes Anglicus ex Maguntia mulier, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tita ſexum,</hi> &amp;c. John Engliſh,<note place="margin">Mitrop. l. <hi>2.</hi> Edit. Colon. <hi>1574.</hi> &amp; Francof. <hi>1590.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:58390:18"/>
               <hi>a Woman of</hi> Mentz, <hi>diſſembled her Sex, and being of a quick wit, and voluble tongue, and one that could talk Scholaſtically, ſhe won the hearts of all men, ſo that ſhe arrived to the dignity of Pope, no Man knowing any other but that ſhe was a Man, ſave one of her Servants, who afterwards got her with Child: they ſay ſhe was deliver'd near the Coloſſes, before ſhe had ſate too years compleat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mantuan,</hi> who is commended by <hi>Trithemius</hi> for an excellent The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ologiſt, a knowing Philoſpher, and a famous Poet, the only man in all <hi>Italy</hi> in his time, hath this ſtory in his deſcription of Hell, and deſcribing what manner of Perſons were there, ſaith he.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hic pendebat adhuc ſexum mentita virilem</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Faemina, cui triplici Phrygiam dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demate, mitram</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Extollebat apex &amp; pontificalis adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:58390:18"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Here hangs a Woman, once who paſt for man,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Who truckt for Breeches, Peticoats, and Fan.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>By her great parts ſhe gain'd, with much renown,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Phrygian Mitre, with the triple Crown.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Here hangs that Lecher too, by whom 'tis ſed</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Woman Pope did loſe her Maiden-head,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And in the Street 'thout Midwife brought to bed.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <hi>Achilles Gaſſarus</hi> in his Epitome of all Hiſtories, and Cronicles, collected out of the beſt Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphers, writs thus<note n="u" place="margin">Achilles Gaſſarus, <hi>in Epit. Hiſt. &amp;c.</hi> Antwerp 1536.</note> John <hi>the eight, by Country Engliſh, by calling a</hi> Pope, <hi>yet by Sex a Woman, ſate ſhamefully as</hi> Pope <hi>two years and ſix Months.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Raviſius Textor,</hi> in his <hi>Officina</hi> writs thus; <hi>Scitum ex Chronicis,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:58390:19"/>&amp; à Majoribus Scriptum Johannem Anglicum ab Ephebis ſexum veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem ſimulaſſe, et tandem fato neſcio quo, aut Fortuna certè volente, ad pontificatum perveniſſe, in quo Annos circiter duos ſederit poſt Leonem quartum, neque prius innotuerit facti veritas, quam à quodam ex domeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis impregnata, tandem emiſerit par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum;</hi> It is a thing well known by the <hi>Cronicles,</hi> and written by our <hi>Anceſtors,</hi> that <hi>John Engliſh,</hi> from her youth upward deported her ſelf in every reſpect like a man, and at length, by I know not what deſtiny, certainly by very great for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune ſhe became <hi>Pope,</hi> and ſate about two years after <hi>Leo the fourth</hi> and no body know this fallaſie and deceit till ſhe was with Child by one of her menial Servants,<note n="a" place="margin">De dictis factiſque me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morabilibus lib. <hi>8.</hi> cap. <hi>3</hi> Tit. de fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis quae doctrinâ excel.</note> and deliver'd thereof: and <hi>Fulgoſus,</hi> who was a noble, and learned man, and ſometimes <hi>Duke of Genua</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms the ſame ſtory for a truth,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:58390:19"/>ſaying, <hi>that John the eight was at length detected to be a Woman.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laziardus</hi> is of the ſame opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſo is <hi>Hartmannus Schedel</hi> a Doctor of Phyſick, yet not ignorant of holy Scriptures, nor atheiſtical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inclined, as it is bewailably common for ſuch ſo to be, yet by <hi>Florimondus</hi> he is accuſed for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one of the brood of the <hi>Huſſites,</hi> and lived in <hi>Nurimberge</hi> when that City was infected with <hi>Huſſes</hi> he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy, and therefore would fain perſwade his party that no credit is to be given him, becauſe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he writ concerning the Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Joan the Woman</hi> was par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial. In anſwèr to this, I rather believe <hi>Florimondus</hi> to be one of the brood of abominable Lyars; for <hi>Hartmannus Schedel,</hi> born in <hi>Nurimberg,</hi> was<note n="b" place="margin">Ego <hi>Hart. Schedel,</hi> Doctor Pata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinus, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> circa Anno <hi>1440.</hi> f. <hi>252.</hi>
               </note> ſtudent in <hi>Padua,</hi> where he was created Doctor of Phyſick by the great <hi>Matthiolus,</hi> and he was ſo far from <hi>Huſſes</hi> opinion,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:58390:20"/>that in the ſame book quoted in the Margent he hath inſerted one whole Chapter about the hereſy of the <hi>Huſſites,</hi> and their original.<note n="z" place="margin">Anthropolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia lib. <hi>22.</hi> pag. <hi>503.</hi> edit. Baſil. <hi>1556.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Volateran,</hi> an Hiſtoriographer of good note, makes no doubt of the reality of this ſtory; and <hi>Trithemius Abbot of St. Martins Monaſtery in Spanheim,</hi> a reverend, well read, and very learned man writes thus, <hi>In the ſame year that Pope Leo died, John Engliſh</hi> ſucceeded for two years and five months. Now ſome ſay ſhe was a Woman, and that ſhe was known ſo to be but to one only, who was her ſervant, by whom at length ſhe was begot with Child, and thereof deliver'd in the open ſtreet. For this cauſe ſome would not reckon her among the number of <hi>Popes,</hi> diſliking this villainous action: with whom, in matter of fact, correſponds <hi>Sabel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licus,</hi> a man<note n="a" place="margin">Sabellicus vir undecun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>; doctiſſimus claret hodiè apud venetos maximo in pretio. Trithe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mius lib. de Script. Eccleſ.</note> of great eſteem in <hi>Venice,</hi> yea the moſt famous in his
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:58390:20"/>time for all manner of learning; of whoſe books, <hi>Pius the Third</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed he valued as much, as <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> did <hi>Homers Iliads.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wernerus Roleunick,</hi> who is rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned by <hi>Paulus Langius</hi> among the moſt famous of the <hi>Order of Carthuſians,</hi> and commended by <hi>Trithemius</hi> for a man of profound learning, and ſingular devotion, in confirmation of what is aforeſaid, writes thus:<note n="b" place="margin">Faſciculus Temp. aetate <hi>6.</hi> ad annum <hi>854.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>This John, by Sir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name, Engliſh, by his Country, of Mentz, is reported to have ſate as Pope about this time; and ſhe was a woman, but went in mans apparel. She pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fited ſo well in Divinity, that ſhe had no fellow, and ſo was choſen to be Pope; But after a while, being great with Child, as ſhe went in publick Proceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſhe was delivered thereof, and dyed. And this ſeems to be the Sixth Pope to this day, which was called Holy and proved naught: And therefore he was plagued by God, as
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:58390:21"/>the reſt before him were plagued, Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is ſhe in the Regiſter of Popes.</hi> Hence ſome ſay, becauſe ſhe was a Germane, a Germane is not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited to be elected Pope, but this is manifeſtly falſe; for ſince, ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Germains have been advanced unto the Popedom.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mattheus Palmerius,</hi> an<note n="c" place="margin">Trithemius de Script. Eccleſiaſt.</note> 
               <hi>Italian,</hi> and one of the choiceſt men which were at the <hi>Council</hi> kept by <hi>Euge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, the</hi> 4. againſt the <hi>Council of Braſil; Pontifex</hi> 106. <hi>Johannes Anglicus</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſedit An.</hi> 2. <hi>Menſ.</hi> 3. <hi>fama eſt hunc Johannem foeminam fuiſſe, et uni ſoli familiari cognitam, qui eam complexus eſt, et gravis facta peperit Papa exiſtens; quamobrem inter Pontifices non nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merant quidam, ideo nomini nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum non facit;</hi> that is <hi>John</hi> was a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, yet not known ſo to be, but to one of her familiars, who lay with her, ſhe was deliver'd in the time of her Papacy, and becauſe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:58390:21"/>ſome reckon her not among the <hi>Popes,</hi> there are no more <hi>Johns</hi> for her, than if ſhe had never been. The account that <hi>B. Platina</hi> gives of this <hi>Learned Whore,</hi> (or as <hi>Mr. Fox</hi> calls her the <hi>Whore of Babylon</hi>) is contradicted by ſome, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be never written by the Author aforeſaid, but foiſted in, ſo <hi>Bernartius</hi> conjectures; and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm his groundleſs ſuppoſition (ſaith he)<note n="d" place="margin">Bernartius de utilitate Legendae, hiſt. lib. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>111.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Antonius Hetweeld,</hi> a man of good report, and Alderman of <hi>Lovaine</hi> told me, that one <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelbertus Boonius,</hi> a reverend Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main Dean had often times told him, that he had ſeen many antient Manuſcripts of <hi>Platina</hi> in the <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tican at Rome,</hi> and perſued them di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently, and yet found not any men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made of this <hi>Pope Joane.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Surely this reverend Dean had the luck on't, to light on ſuch anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Manuſcripts, as the <hi>Alderman of Lovain</hi> informed <hi>Bernartius</hi> of,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:58390:22"/>but how comes it about, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Onuphrius, Platina</hi>'s <hi>Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tator, Bellarmin,</hi> nor <hi>Baronius,</hi> who have had as free acceſs into the <hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tican Library,</hi> as any, could never light on theſe Manuſcripts as well as he? And how comes it that none ſince <hi>Bernartius</hi> thought good to except in that manner againſt <hi>Platina,</hi> the acknowledgment of thoſe too Pillars of the <hi>Romiſh Church, Bellarmin</hi> and <hi>Baronius,</hi> with <hi>Onuphrius,</hi> that this Story is originally in <hi>Platina</hi> induceth me to believe, that, either <hi>Bernartius,</hi> belyed the <hi>Alderman,</hi> or the <hi>Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> belyed the reverend <hi>Dean,</hi> or the <hi>Dean</hi> made a Fool of the <hi>Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> and made the other ſo too by conſequence: for queſtionleſs had there been any ſuch Manuſcripts, ſome of them would have found them out, and made them publick to wipe off that infamy they more than barely ſtand ſuſpected of. For
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:58390:22"/>they are glad of narrower <hi>Fig-tree-leaves</hi> to cover their <hi>Nakedneſs</hi> withal, than ſuch Manuſcripts, could they be produced.</p>
            <p>Now ſince it is evident, that <hi>Platina</hi> did write the life of this <hi>Lady Errant Joan,</hi> who coming from <hi>Athens</hi> became at <hi>Rome</hi> a teeming <hi>Pope,</hi> the Romaniſts have indeavour'd to find another hole to creep out at, denying that he writ by publick authority, and did not take his Hiſtory out of the publick Regiſters of the Church. The belief hereof is an errour, and a groſs one too; for<note n="e" place="margin">Prooemio lib. de Vitis Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tif. in Epiſtola ad Ziſtum. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Platina</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf profeſſeth, that he writ by the command of <hi>Sixtus the fourth;</hi> and <hi>Onuphrius</hi> confeſſeth, that he fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed <hi>Damaſus, Anaſtatius,</hi> and ſuch Hiſtorigraphers, as had writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten before of the ſame matter. I but ſays <hi>Florimondus, Platina</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported it rather to ſhew his read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, than for that he thought it
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:58390:23"/>true, for, (ſays he) had he ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin'd it true, he would have exag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerated it, and made the worſt on't, that thereby he might have reveng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf of the Popes, at whom he was grievouſly incenſed. For <hi>Paul the Second</hi> (continues he which all men know) racked him, and deveſted him, of all his digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and juſtly caſting him into Priſon, kept him there as long as himſelf lived. To this I anſwer; that he was racked, and impriſoned by <hi>Paul the Second,</hi> is true, but that it was juſtly done, is falſe; for <hi>Trithemius</hi> chargeth that <hi>Pope</hi> for ſo doing with cruelty.</p>
            <p>Yet ſuppoſe all were true, doth it follow in <hi>Florimondus</hi> Logick, that becauſe <hi>Paul the</hi> II. wronged <hi>Plati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na; ergo, Platina</hi> hated all Popes? and why not then; <hi>Sixtus the fourth</hi> gratified <hi>Platina</hi> many ways, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him at Liberty, and reſtoring him his dignities; <hi>ergo Platina</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:58390:23"/>Loved all <hi>Popes</hi> for his ſake? If one mans Kindneſs could not work Love towards all, it is not likely that one mans unkindneſs ſhould breed hatred or Heart-burning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all; wherefore notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this we may well think, that <hi>Platina</hi> wrote what he thought, and the rather for that in the words following, he profeſſeth,<note n="f" place="margin">Apparet ea quae dixi ex his eſſe, qui fieri poſſe creduntur lib. <hi>6.</hi> pag. <hi>98.</hi>
               </note> that ſuch a thing may likely hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen.</p>
            <p>That I may not ſeem deficient in the production of teſtimonies for the farther probation of this ſtory, give me leave to inſert ſome more; amongſt none of the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, obſerve what <hi>Chalcocondelas</hi> ſays, <hi>It is well known that a certain woman was made</hi> Pope, <hi>by reaſon they knew not her Sex. For all (almoſt) in the Weſtern parts of Italy, ſhave their beards. Now when ſhe was great with child, and came abroad to ſolemnize ſome day, or to ſay ſervice;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:58390:24"/>as ſhe was at ſervice, ſhe was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd of a Child in the ſight of all the People. Wherefore leſt hereafter they ſhould be deceived in like ſort, they make tryal of his man-hood by touching, and he that toucheth proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, <hi>We have a man to our Pope.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe words are allowed by them to be in the <hi>Latin Tranſlation,</hi> but<note n="g" place="margin">Annal. Tom. <hi>10.</hi> ad annum <hi>853.</hi> num. <hi>66.</hi> Quamvis apud Chalco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condilum La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinè redditum ejuſmodi fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bula reperitur eſſe deſcripta; non tamen ab ipſo Authore poſitum ſcias ſed ab Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore Clauſere fraudulenter appoſitum.</note> 
               <hi>Baronius</hi> will not admit of them in the <hi>Greek;</hi> for, (ſays he) <hi>Clauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> his interpreter, added in his tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation this ſtory, which is not to be found in the Greek Copy: and for further perſwaſion, to make men believe it, he ſays, that <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimondus</hi> hath excellently well diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered the couſonage of <hi>Clauſerus,</hi> for comparing <hi>Clauſerus</hi> tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Latin, with a Frenchmans tranſlation of the ſame in his Mother Tongue, by that he found the Tale was not in <hi>Calcocondilas;</hi> for there was not one word of it in the <hi>French</hi> tranſlation. But
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:58390:24"/>why I pray may not the <hi>French man</hi> leave it out as well as <hi>Clauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus;</hi> it may be objected (but how truly I know not) that this French man was a faithful tranſlator, and durſt not have left it out, if he had found it in the Greek, as <hi>Florimon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> notes. And why may we not hold <hi>Clauſerus</hi> as faithful an interpreter as the <hi>Frenchman,</hi> yea more faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, ſeeing the <hi>French man</hi> was a <hi>Papiſt:</hi> for<note n="i" place="margin">Gretſer lib. <hi>2.</hi> de jure, &amp;c. prohib. lib. malos cap. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Papiſts</hi> hold it Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in tranſlating to omit offenſive matter, and ſo doth no <hi>Proteſtant.</hi> If <hi>Florimondus,</hi> or <hi>Baronius</hi> could have informed us where a man might have ſeen a Greek Copy in which it is not, they had ſaid ſomething to purpoſe, but to go about to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove it by a tranſlation of one of their own creatures, they argue ridiculouſly, and if any of them gainſay that in the Weſtern parts of <hi>Italy</hi> all (almoſt) ſhave not<note n="h" place="margin">Fidus Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pres praeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittere non auſus fuiſſet, ſi in Graeco Exemplari exeratum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniſſet.</note>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:58390:25"/>their Beards, as ſome have made that vain oppoſition, it is eaſily anſwered: for by the <hi>Popes Canons,</hi> the <hi>Italian Prieſts,</hi> yea all the Prieſts of the Weſtern Church are to be ſhaven; ſo ſaith<note n="k" place="margin">Chronogr. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Pontacus, hic Papa (Anicetus) Clericos comam &amp; barbam radere in ſignum clerica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus juſſit.</hi> Pope Anicetus <hi>command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Clergy to ſhave both their heads and their beards, in token that they were of the Clergy.</hi> And, <hi>Occi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentalis eccleſiae clerum, ab ipſis ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae Chriſtianae primordiis barbam radendi morem tenuiſſe, aſserit Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorius</hi> 7. Pope Gregory <hi>the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth avouceth, that from the Apoſtles days the Weſtern Clergy did ſhave their beards, to whom</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Rational. Divin. Offic. lib. <hi>2.</hi> de Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtris, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Durandus who lived about the year</hi> 1280, <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth:</hi> for he acknowledgeth that before, and in his time, they were ſhaved, proving the lawfulneſs of it out of <hi>Ezechiel,</hi> and ſhewing the myſteries that are imported by
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:58390:25"/>it. <hi>Johannes Pierius Valerianus,</hi> atteſts the ſame, imputing the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of electing <hi>Pope Joan</hi> to the ordinary ſhaving of Beards, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by that means one could hardly know a man from a woman, which cuſtom is ſhamefully revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in theſe fantaſtical times among our gentry, whoſe cloſe ſhav'd wither'd Countenances, are no ways diſtinguiſhable from an anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitated Gentlewoman, but by their long Wigs, which ſeem to hide thoſe imperfections which attend on age.</p>
            <p>For further proof of the verity of this ſtory, it well be expedient to give you an account what <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricus de Niem</hi> (Secretary to a Pope) relates:<note n="m" place="margin">De Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiis &amp; juri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Imperii.</note> 
               <hi>John, called Engliſh, was a woman born at</hi> Mentz, <hi>and ſhe ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died at</hi> Athens, <hi>apparel'd like a man, where ſhe profited ſo well in the Arts, that coming to</hi> Rome <hi>ſhe read there the liberal ſciences and was held, ſo ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:58390:26"/>a Reader, that many of the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſort became her hearers; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards with one conſent ſhe was choſen</hi> Pope, <hi>and lived in that dignity two years, and upwards: But taking her ſelf more than before to idleneſs, and pleaſure, ſhe could not live ſo conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently as ſhe did, in her mean, yet ſtudious condition: whereupon one day as ſhe went with the Clergy, and People of</hi> Rome <hi>(according to the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of that time) in ſolemn Proceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, being attired in the uſual Papal ornaments, ſhe was delivered of her firſt begotten ſon (the Father whereof was her ſervant) near the Temple of Peace, which ſtands in the City; as it is evident by an old Marble Image which ſtands there to this day, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>note ſo much in a figure. And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon it is that when the</hi> Popes <hi>go from the Vatican to St. John Laterans, and back again, they go not the direct way thither but by other ſtreets farther about, and ſo make their journey lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:58390:26"/>
            <p>I ſhall relate nothing what <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarch, Boccace, Lucidus,</hi> and our Country-man <hi>Higden</hi> ſays to this purpoſe, ſince there are none ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate, but will confeſs they all have writ thereof, but only a little touch upon what<note n="n" place="margin">Trithem. de Script. Eccleſ. &amp; Poſſevinus in Apparatu Sacro verbo, <hi>Johan. Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſienſis.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>John of Paris</hi> writes as to this matter, who lived about the year 1280. and read publickly in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity of Paris,</hi> with great, and deſerved commendation, as well in Divinity, as Humanity: he ſhowing how ſometimes a man may lawfully diſpute, and take excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt the <hi>Pope,</hi> in reſpect of his Perſon<note n="o" place="margin">De Pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate Regia &amp; Papali.</note> notes, that ſuch a Perſon may be choſen as is not capable: <hi>ut ſi eſſ et foemina, vel Haereticus, ſicut fuerunt aliqui qui ob hoc non enumer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantur in Catalogo Paparum.</hi> As for example (ſaith he) if he prove a Woman, or an Heretick, as ſome have done, who in that reſpect are not reckoned in the <hi>Catalogue</hi> of the <hi>Popes.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:58390:27"/>
            <p>What an infinite number of wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes could I produce to verify this ſtory whoſe Teſtimonies though ever ſo clear, yet the Romaniſts, the oppoſers of truth, will cavil at. <hi>Martinus Polonus,</hi> becauſe he hath writ the truth concerning <hi>Pope Joane</hi> (for no other reaſon that I can find) they call him ſimple, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant man, given to vanity, and only famous for fables, for that is<note n="p" place="margin">Martinus Polonus fabu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis tantum ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebris, caetero obſcurus homo.</note> 
               <hi>Bernartius</hi> his cenſure of him. See the raſhneſs of our later genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Papiſts;</hi> for<note n="q" place="margin">Archiep. Cofentinus &amp; Paenitentiari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Papae. Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Appara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ſacer verbo Marti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Polonus.</note> 
               <hi>Polonus</hi> was an Arch-Biſhop, and <hi>Penitentiary</hi> to the <hi>Pope;</hi> he was learned in the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> and not ignorant of ſecular learning; he was one, whom <hi>Platina</hi> relyed on much for matter of hiſtory and applauded by him for a man of a good life, and converſation. He was the man, whom the Author of <hi>Faſciculus Temporum,</hi> and <hi>Jacobus Bergomenſis,</hi> two good Hiſtoriographers, profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:58390:27"/>that they followed eſpecially; and yet he is abuſed with undeſerved titles of ignorance, for ſpeaking the truth.</p>
            <p>The premiſes conſider'd, one would think there needed no other quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations for farther proof of a matter ſo notorious, however ſince we have ſuch plenty of Teſtimonies, it will not be irrequiſit to inſert ſome more, that may for ever ſtop the mouths of Truths objectors and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poners: and firſt, <hi>Marianus Scotus,</hi> who was born in the year 1028.<note n="r" place="margin">Ab omnibus honore habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur &amp; non ſine opinione ſanctitatis ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelitur, Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>themius de Script. Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiasticis.</note> a man of eſtimation whilſt he lived, and when dead, was held a <hi>Saint,</hi> and by <hi>Baronius</hi> was ſtiled, <hi>Nobilis Chronographus,</hi> a worthy <hi>Chonologer;</hi> in his Chronicle, thus we read, <hi>Leo Papa obiit Kalend. Auguſti, huic ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cceſſit Joanna mulier An.</hi> 2. <hi>Menſ.</hi> 5. <hi>dieb.</hi> 4. that is <hi>Leo the Pope dyed in the Kalends of Auguſt. after him ſucceeded</hi> Joane <hi>the woman, who ſate</hi> 2 <hi>years</hi> 5 <hi>Months and</hi> 4 <hi>days:</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Lib. <hi>4.</hi> de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Rom. Pont. cap. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmin</hi>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:58390:28"/>contradicts this, ſaying, that he who publiſhed <hi>Krantius Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolis</hi> at <hi>Colen</hi> in the year 1574. doth witneſs; <hi>in antiquiſſimis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplaribus Mariani Scoti non haberi Johannem Papam foeminam: that in the antient copies of Marianus Sco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, there is no mention made of Pope Joane the woman:</hi> What this <hi>He</hi> ſhould be, that gives this Teſtimony, I never yet could learn, nor that he was a man of any credit, beſides, there is no reaſon that a <hi>nameleſs Sr. Mr. Anonymus</hi> ſhould be credited againſt all printed Copies, eſpecially if it be true, which<note n="t" place="margin">Lib. <hi>4.</hi> de Rom. Pont. Cap. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bellarmin</hi> ſaith in another caſe: <hi>Author ſine no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine eſt ſine authoritate: a man with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a name is without credit;</hi> and <hi>Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus a concilio cujus ne nomen quidem extet facile contemni poteſt: a Canon out of a Councill, whoſe name is not known may very well be ſlighted.</hi> But would you know the reaſon why <hi>Bellarmin</hi> did not name him?
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:58390:28"/>you may ſuppoſe, not becauſe he was ignorant of his name, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was but a mean fellow, a Printer, a poor Batchelour of the Law, a man of ſlender reputation; for he is named in the firſt page of the <hi>Book Gerwinus Calenius Lippi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enſis:</hi> and what was ſuch a fellow to run away with a ſtory of this conſequence upon his bare word in this manner; <hi>n quae hic Author de Johanne foemina refert, in odium Romanorum Pontificum confict a fuiſſe ab illis quos ipſe deceptus ſequitur ut alios omittamus quos Onuphrius in Platinam ſcribens recenſet, teſtantur Marianus Scotus &amp; Sigibertus, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum quae ſuperſunt M. S. exemplaria fraudem illorum detegunt, qui eorum impreſſis voluminibus id inſeruerunt. That this which the Author hereof re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports touching</hi> Pope Joan <hi>is but coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit ſtuff, deviſed to make the Pope odious; to ſay nothing of ſuch proofs as</hi> Onuphrius <hi>gives in his Annotations on</hi> Platina, Martianus, Scotus, <hi>&amp;</hi> Sigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,<note n="u" place="margin">Annotat in lib. <hi>2.</hi> Kran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tii Metrop.</note>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:58390:29"/>
               <hi>do teſtify; whoſe manuſcripts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining on record diſcover their falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood who have chopt his tale into their printed volumes;</hi> which <hi>Bellarmin,</hi> nor any other durſt or dare avouch, the contrary being confeſs'd direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by <hi>Baronius:</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">In chronico ad An. <hi>184</hi> Printed at Paris. <hi>1513.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sigiberts</hi> words are theſe, <hi>The report is, that this</hi> John <hi>was a woman, and that one only, who laid with her, knew ſo much: and that at length, even in the time of her Papacy, ſhe was delivered of a Child. Whereupon it is that ſome reckon her not among the</hi> Popes, <hi>and that there is not one</hi> Pope John <hi>the more in number for her.</hi> Notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this, the Romaniſts deny that there is any ſuch thing in the anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, true, and approved Copies of <hi>Sigibert,</hi> and if there be any ſuch thing found, ſome paltry fellow, (as <hi>Bernartius</hi> notes) hath been tampering with his writings, and that <hi>Sigibert</hi> never writ it is fully witneſſed by <hi>Genebrard.</hi> Pray here obſerve, the <hi>Canoniſts</hi> (when <hi>Popes</hi>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:58390:29"/>alledge <hi>Popes</hi> for proof) do note, that it is <hi>familiaris probatio;</hi> mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it may be as much as that in the Proverb, <hi>Ask my fellow if I be a Thief.</hi> But ſay they in the Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of <hi>Gemble</hi> in <hi>Flanders</hi> there is extant the Original of <hi>Sigibert,</hi> which wants this Story, and for proof hereof, they have the oath of one <hi>Protaſius</hi> a Franciſcan, who ſaw it, and there (as he ſaith) <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibert</hi> lived, there he wrote this <hi>Book</hi> with his own hands, there he left it after life as a Monument of his love. There it is ſhown by the Monks to ſuch as come thither for a piece of excellency and rarity.</p>
            <p>Now judge you whether this paltry <hi>Fryer</hi> is to be believed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Trithemius,</hi> who 0436 0106 V 3 (ſays he) lived not there when he writ the <hi>Book;</hi> for he writ that, and many others in the Monaſtery of <hi>St. Vincent</hi> within the city of <hi>Metenſis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Monks</hi> ſhewing this <hi>Book</hi> as <hi>Sigiberts</hi> own to all comers, is<note n="y" place="margin">De Scripto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticis Sigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertus cum in Caenobio. <hi>8.</hi> Vincentio Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſi ad in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruend. pue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roseſſer poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus ſcripſit. Hiſt. lib.</note>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:58390:30"/>a very ſlender argument to prove that it is his: for I have read of a<note n="z" place="margin">Vergerius Annot. in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talog. haeret. Romae confla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum An. <hi>1559</hi> fol. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Monk</hi> who gave out that he had brought from the Eaſt ſome of the ſound of the Bells which hung in <hi>Solomons Temple,</hi> and<note n="*" place="margin">ibid.</note> that he could ſhew among other reliques, ſome of the hairs which fell from the <hi>Seraphical Angel</hi> when he came to imprint the <hi>Five wounds</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in St. <hi>Francis</hi>'s body, and I have<note n="*" place="margin">Bellonius obſer: lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>33.</hi>
               </note> read of others who ſhew the Pilgrims who go to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> a three corner'd ſtone, aſſuring them it is that very ſtone whereof <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> ſpoak, ſaying, <hi>The ſtone which the Builders refuſed, is the head of the corner. Pſal.</hi> 118.22.</p>
            <p>Now as Monks and Papiſts cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen others, ſo they are often cheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves; for many of them do verily believe they have that which they have not. Do not many of them perſwade them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that they have that <hi>Syndon</hi> wherein <hi>Chriſts</hi> body was lapped,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:58390:30"/>when it was interred, wherein (as they ſay) is to be ſeen to this day the Picture of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Others think they have the <hi>Nails</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with <hi>Chriſt</hi> was nailed to the <hi>Croſs,</hi> and in like manner are they decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in a thouſand ſeveral ſorts of reliques.</p>
            <p>But grant that this ſtory of <hi>Pope Joan</hi> is not to be found in ſome Copies of <hi>Sigibert,</hi> that does not argue that it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver writ by him; it is probable it may be left out by ſome, who have tranſcribed his Manuſcript, which we may as well be induced to believe, and upon as good grounds, as that the words of <hi>Aelfricus,</hi> which oppoſe Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation were cut out of a frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of an Epiſtle of his in the Library of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> as<note n="a" place="margin">Act. &amp; Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num. allegati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons againſt the <hi>6.</hi> Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, Pag. <hi>1304.</hi> edit. <hi>1570.</hi>
               </note> Mr. <hi>Fox</hi> doth prove apparently. Thus is this ſtory of <hi>Pope Joan</hi> cut out of a very fair Manuſcript of <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulfus
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:58390:31"/>Ceſtrenſis</hi> which is now to be ſeen in the Library of <hi>New-Colledge</hi> in <hi>Oxford:</hi> we need not wonder at ſuch unjuſt proceedings of the Papiſts, ſince they give dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, that,<note n="b" place="margin">Index lib. prohib. per Clementem <hi>8.</hi> de Correct. lib.</note> 
               <hi>qua famae proximorum, &amp; praeſertim Eccleſiaſticorum, &amp; Principum detrahunt, corrigentur, atque expurgentur. That ſuch things ſhould be alter'd, or put out, which tend to the Diſcredit of the Clergy;</hi> and doth not this touch their Eccleſiaſtick eſtate to the very quick? doth not <hi>Poſſevin</hi> adviſe, that the<note n="c" place="margin">Joh. Nevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Sylva Nuptialis. pag. <hi>319.</hi>
               </note> note in <hi>John Neviſon</hi> the Lawyer, which makes mention of <hi>Pope Joan</hi> ſhould be razed out? <hi>Dele</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>quia Johannes haec foemina Chimaera eſt, &amp; impoſtura calumniatorum;</hi> blot it out (ſaith <hi>Poſſevin</hi>) becauſe <hi>John</hi> this <hi>Woman</hi> was a meer <hi>Chimaera,</hi> and a forgery of Calumniators.</p>
            <p>For further proof that this <hi>John</hi> was a meer fiction <hi>Cardinal Baro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:58390:31"/>would make us believe, that thoſe of the beſt Credit in Hiſtory, and who have writ moſt of her, do not poſitively aver that there was ſuch a <hi>Woman Pope,</hi> but make their report of her with a <hi>ſic aiunt,</hi> or an <hi>ut aſſeritur,</hi> but he brings no other proof thereof than <hi>teſte me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſo:</hi> which however it may go for proof among <hi>Princes,</hi> yet is no proof among <hi>Scholars:</hi> and for my part without proof I will believe nothing, let who will be the aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, eſpecially if he be a Papiſt. For as<note n="d" place="margin">Rerum Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morab. Parali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pom. Hiſt. Abbat <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſperg. annexa. pag. <hi>394.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sigiſmund</hi> the Emperour ſaid of <hi>Julian</hi> the Cardinal Legate at the <hi>Council of Baſil,</hi> when one commended him highly to him; <hi>tamen Romanus eſt;</hi> yea but he is a Roman; ſo I may ſay of any Romaniſt reporting things un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known, yea but he is a Romaniſt, or Papiſt.</p>
            <p>And now I pray ſuppoſe it be ſo as <hi>Baronius</hi> ſaith it is, why may
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:58390:32"/>it not be true though it be deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with an <hi>ut aſſeritur?</hi> It may be objected that Lyes and falſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports are midwiv'd into the world after that manner with, <hi>ſo ſome ſay,</hi> and <hi>thus it is ſaid.</hi> I confeſs that many lies, nay groſs ones too, paſs in ſuch general terms: as for example. <hi>Men ſay</hi> (ſaith the Popiſh Golden Legend) <hi>that St. Patrick drove with his ſtaff all the venemous Beaſts out of Ireland; and, that he obtein'd of the Lord, that no Iriſh man ſhould abide the coming of Anti-chriſt:</hi> the former of which <hi>Harpfield Cope</hi> confeſſeth to be a Lye, and ſo I think all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding Papiſts acknowledg the latter; elſe why do none of the learned Clergy of the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> alledg it, to clear the <hi>Pope</hi> from being <hi>Anti-chriſt.</hi> Men ſay (ſaith <hi>Nangiacus,</hi> as <hi>Genebrard</hi> reporteth) that Kentiſh men have tails like bruit Beaſts,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:58390:32"/>becauſe their Anceſtors mocked <hi>Auſtin</hi> the <hi>Monk</hi> when he came to preach among them; nay by ſome this is believed as a truth to this day, for but lately a Kentiſh-man traveling with a <hi>Fleming,</hi> and being conſtrain'd to lye together, the <hi>Dutchman</hi> would not go to bed till he had ſatiſfied his Eyes with the truth, or falſhood of a <hi>Kentiſh-long-tail;</hi> that this is a lye, there is nothing more evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and yet this is reported with a, <hi>ſo 'tis ſaid.</hi> When <hi>Boniface the Martyr</hi> was demanded whether it was Lawful to uſe a wooden chalice at the adminiſtration of the Lords ſupper; it is ſaid he anſwered thus (ſaith<note n="e" place="margin">De ſacris Eccleſiaſt. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefic. ac Min. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Duaren</hi>) <hi>Olim aurei Sacerdotes ligneis va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, nunc lignei aureis utuntur: In former times Golden Prieſts uſed Wooden Chalices, now Wooden Prieſts uſe Golden ones:</hi> in like manner it was written that <hi>Pius</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:58390:33"/>the 2. was wont to ſay, <hi>Marriage upon juſt reaſon was forbidden Prieſts, but now upon better reaſon to be reſtored to them again:</hi> of which ſaying of his there is no queſtion to be made, as may appear by this, that<note n="f" place="margin">Piſanus de Continentia cap. <hi>ii.</hi>
               </note> a <hi>Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it</hi> only thus replies, <hi>That it was</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canted by him, <hi>and denieth not that it was ſpoken by him.</hi> That <hi>Alexander the third</hi> trampled the <hi>Emperour Frederick</hi> under his feet, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded one to ſay, <hi>thou ſhalt walk up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lyon, and aſp, the young Lyon, and the Dragon ſhalt thou tread under thy feet Pſal.</hi> 91.13.<note n="g" place="margin">Duaremus de ſac. Eccl. Min. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> this is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported with an, <hi>ut fertur,</hi> and yet they have little to ſay for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves who call the truth thereof into queſtion. That merry <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal,</hi> who ſeeing after the death of <hi>Clement the fourth,</hi> that his <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren</hi> the <hi>Cardinals</hi> called ſtill for the aſſiſtance of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and could not agree upon the election of a new <hi>Pope,</hi> cryed out<note n="h" place="margin">Onuph. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notat in Plat. de vitis Pon. tif. in vit. Gregorii <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Domini
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:58390:33"/>diſco operiamus tectum camerae hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus, quia Spiritus Sanctus nequit ad nos per tot tecta ingredi; Sirs, let us untile the roof of this room; for I fear the Holy Ghoſt cannot get to us through ſo many ſlates:</hi> this is meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note n="i" place="margin">Onuphr. ib.</note> reported upon election of <hi>Gego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> to have made theſe Verſes.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Papatus munus tulit Archidiaconus unus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quem Patrem Patrum fecit di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcordia fratrum.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Diſput. ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per mater. Conc. gen. quae habetur in Faſciculo Rerum. expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend. Col. <hi>15 35.</hi> fol. <hi>21.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Nicholas Clemangis</hi> Arch Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con of <hi>Baion</hi> in <hi>France</hi> writes upon hearſay, that when <hi>Balthaſar,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly known by the name of <hi>John the</hi> 23. held a <hi>Council</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> and cauſed, according to cuſtom, before the firſt Seſſion A <hi>Maſs</hi> to be ſaid for the aſſiſtance of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt;</hi> immediatly upon the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils</hi> ſitting, and <hi>Balthaſars</hi> advancing himſelf into the <hi>Chair of State;</hi> an Owl, of a prodigious bigneſs (an evil preſage) came out of a hole
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:58390:34"/>whooping and hollowing after a dreadful manner, and flew to the middle balk of the Church, ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring juſt in <hi>Balthaſar</hi>'s face, to the great aſtoniſhment of him, and the whole <hi>Council,</hi> which immediately hereupon broke up. He further writes, that at the next Seſſion ſhe appear'd again, ſtaring in the <hi>Popes</hi> face as before, and could not be frighted away with what extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary noiſe was made for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; at length one throwing a ſtick knockt her down, and killed her. No man will queſtion the truth hereof, ſince he confeſſeth, that he had this ſtory of a faithful friend, who aſſured him it was true upon his credit. That the worſt <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in <hi>Italy</hi> are the <hi>Romans;</hi> that of the <hi>Romans,</hi> the <hi>Prieſts</hi> are moſt wicked; and of the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> the lewdeſt are made <hi>Cardinals,</hi> and the baddeſt choſen to be <hi>Pope;</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Sir. Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Sands of the Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on uſed in the Weſt, pag. <hi>91.</hi>
               </note> it is written but with, <hi>aſſeritur:</hi>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:58390:34"/>yet to the skilful in Hiſtory, and ſuch as are acquainted with the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of <hi>Rome,</hi> this doth not ſeem improbable. <hi>In Bavaria palam ferunt Jeſuitas dolium in Collegium ſubvex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe, è cujus fundo effracto, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retrix in publicas plateas prolapſa ſit</hi> (ſaith<note n="m" place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> de verbo dei cap. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Haſſen Muller</hi>) <hi>They ſay openly in Bavaria, that the Jeſuits cauſed a Tub to be carried to their Colledge, which breaking by the way, a Wench dropt out of the end on't into the open ſtreet:</hi> And why may not this be true, though it go but by report. The Papiſts believe far more incredible reports than this, which tend to the defamation of us Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>If any ſhould object, that there were many learned men, and great Writers who lived in her time, ſometime after, who though they were the Authors of ſeveral books, yet make no mention of any <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> that was ever <hi>Pope</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:58390:35"/>Beſides <hi>Rupertus,</hi> an Engliſh Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, who, becauſe he was excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated by the <hi>Pope,</hi> invented, and raked together all manner of lyes againſt the <hi>Pope,</hi> yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding objected not this.</p>
            <p>This objection may be eaſily anſwered thus in a word: That moſt of all thoſe Authors who are quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Romaniſts to have made no mention of <hi>Pope Joane</hi> were no hiſtoriographers, but ſuch who em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy'd their Pen, and time in the ſtudy of Philoſophy, or Divinity, and therefore it is no more a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that theſe learned men ſhould be ſilent, as to this matter, than for a Mathematician to write of <hi>Lines</hi> and <hi>Tangents</hi> only, and not to write of <hi>Pharmacy,</hi> and <hi>Phyſick.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, this <hi>Rupertus</hi> (comonly called <hi>Groſthead</hi>) well skil'd in Greek and Latin, a Reader of Divinity in the Schools, an excellent Preacher, and a man ſo eminent for a holy life
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:58390:35"/>and converſation, that it was the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of the whole Clergy of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> that there was not ſuch another among the Prelates of that time; yet <hi>Innocent the fourth</hi> call'd him<note n="n" place="margin">Quis eſt ille delirus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſurdus &amp; abſurdus ſaith Innocent the fourth. Mat. Paris.</note> 
               <hi>Old Fool,</hi> ſurd, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd fellow, and his reproaches were attended with menaces. The reaſon is apparent in that he oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the <hi>Pope,</hi> and had divers cavils with him, in ſo much that in one Letter he did not ſtick to tell him plainly, <q>That by his Writs (with (<hi>non obſtante</hi>) he brought a deluge of miſchiefs on the world, whereby the purity of the Church was defiled, and the quietneſs of the Republick im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peded and deſtroyed: that by his Reſervations, commendoes, and Proviſions of Benefices for Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who ſought to fleece, and not to feed the flock of God, he commited ſuch a ſin, ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Doctrine of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:58390:36"/>and Evangeliſts, ſo hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and deteſtable, ſo abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to Chriſt Jeſus, as never Sin was, but the Sin of <hi>Lucifer,</hi> nor never ſhall be but the Sin of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti-chriſt,</hi> whom the Lord ſhall deſtroy with the Breath of his Mouth at his coming. He fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſignified that no man could with a good conſcience o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey any ſuch mandates as he ſent abroad, though they came from the higheſt order of Angels: for they tended not to edification, but the utter ruin of the Church.</q> Are theſe Lyes, by reporting whereof he ſought to revenge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf on that preſent <hi>Pope?</hi> Sure it cannot be, ſince the<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t vera fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teamur vera ſunt quae dicit ſaid the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals, Mat. Paris. p <hi>1192</hi>
               </note> Colledge of Cardinals confeſſed before the <hi>Pope,</hi> that they could not blame him for writing thus, having ſaid nothing but what was juſtifiable. And here give me leave to recite what another, <hi>Matthew Paris,</hi> hath
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:58390:36"/>regiſtred to poſterity concerning Popes and Papiſts. In his Hiſtory of <hi>England,</hi> in the life of <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour, in the year 1072, <hi>page</hi> 10. he reports how <hi>Satanas, &amp; omnes contubernium inferorum;</hi> that the Devil and all his helliſh crue writ Letters gratulatory to all the rabble of the Romiſh Clergy, acknowledging their kindneſs, in that following their pleaſures, and deſiſting from inſtructing the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, they ſuffer'd more Souls to go to Hell than ever went before.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Ibid. An. <hi>1074.</hi>
               </note>That <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeventh ſet the whole Church in an uprore by depoſing married prieſts from their prieſthood, and forbidding the Laity to hear them ſay ſervice, becauſe he had no preſident for ſo doing, and becauſe as ſome thought it was unadviſedly done, contrary to the opinion of the antient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who wrote that the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Church, by the invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:58390:37"/>working of the Spirit have like effect, whether they be admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred by good or bad men.<note n="q" place="margin">In Hen. <hi>1.</hi> ad An. <hi>1125.</hi> pag. <hi>93.</hi>
               </note> He reports how a Cardinal Legate, at a Council held in <hi>London</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veighing againſt the Miſſes or Wenches of the Clergy, was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the ſame night after in bed with a Whore or <hi>Bona Roba.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="r" place="margin">In Hen. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>617.</hi>
               </note>He reports, how <hi>Germanus,</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the Cardinals of <hi>Rome,</hi> that the Grecians ſtumbled much at this, that the Cardinals deſired to be accounted his Diſciples, who ſaid, Silver and Gold have I none, and yet none ſo rich, and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous as they.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">In Hen. <hi>3.</hi> pag. <hi>712.</hi> ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>1240.</hi>
               </note>He reports how the Pope en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joined by one mandate to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of <hi>Canterbury, Lincoln,</hi> and <hi>Salisbury,</hi> that they ſhould provide for 300. Romans in Benefices next vacant; and that they ſhould diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of no Benefice, till ſo many
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:58390:37"/>were compleatly provided for.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="t" place="margin">In Hen. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>1089.</hi>
               </note>He reports, how <hi>Hugh the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal</hi> brag'd, when <hi>Innocentius</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from <hi>Lions,</hi> that whereas there were four Stews, or Bawdy-houſes at his coming thither, he had left them but one, and that reached but from one end of the Town to the other.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="u" place="margin">In Hen. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>1100.</hi>
               </note>He reports, how the <hi>Franci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcans</hi> and <hi>Minorites</hi> by Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from the <hi>Pope</hi> appointed all ſorts of people, young and old, men and women, ſound &amp; ſick, and of all conditions, to go for recovery of the <hi>Holy Land,</hi> and yet the ſame day, or a little time after, for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney diſmiſſed them again.</p>
            <p>He reports, how <hi>Innocentius the fourth</hi> inſtigated the people of <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant</hi> and <hi>Flanders</hi> to commence a War againſt <hi>Conradus</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, promiſing them for ſo doing forgiveneſs of all their ſins; yea, not only a pardon for their own
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:58390:38"/>ſins, but the like for their Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>Theſe, and the like ſtories he records againſt the <hi>Pope</hi> being ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuducted thereunto by Truth it ſelf; but he meddles not with any thing which was done by any <hi>Pope</hi> within 1000. years after <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and therefore it is no wonder that he ſpeaks nothing of <hi>Pope Joane.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That I may not omit any materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al object ion that the Romaniſts al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to diſprove the verity of the ſtory of <hi>Pope Joan,</hi> I muſt here in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the <hi>Reader,</hi> that as they ſay many learned Latin writers ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of Her, ſo Greek Hiſtorio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphers, <hi>Zonoras, Cedrenus Caro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palatas,</hi> and others who wrote be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Martinus Polonus</hi> concerning the Latin Church, and were enemies to the ſame, and would have been glad of ſuch an advantage againſt it, write nothing thereof at all; from whence ſome infer there was no ſuch matter.</p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:58390:38"/>
            <p>To ſhape an anſwer to this ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument I muſt beg this queſtion; doth not <hi>Platina</hi> confeſs there was a <hi>Pope</hi> called <hi>Mark,</hi> who ſate two years, eight months, and ten days; and another <hi>Pope</hi> called <hi>Marcellus,</hi> who ſate above five years; and yet<note n="w" place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> Chronogr.</note> 
               <hi>Pontacus,</hi> and<note n="x" place="margin">Chronol. lib. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Genebrard</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that all the Greek Writers in a manner omit to ſpeak of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer; and that all Greek Writers without exception omit to ſpeak of the latter. Now if we ſhould be perſwaded (notwithſtanding their paſſing by theſe inſilence) that theſe were <hi>Popes,</hi> why may we not as well believe that there was a <hi>Pope Joane,</hi> though they paſs her by in like manner, not ſpeaking one word of her: we may believe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things of which they write not a ſyllable. We read in the <hi>Golden Legend,</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Breviar. Rom. in offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio exalt. S. Crucis.</note> 
               <hi>Breviary, &amp;c.</hi> that <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raclius</hi> the Emperour, when he would have entred in by the gate, by which our <hi>Saviour,</hi> went to his
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:58390:39"/>
               <hi>Paſſion,</hi> clad in his Royal robes with the <hi>Croſs</hi> on his ſhoulders, was mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculouſly hindred, and could not get through, til he had deveſted his body of it's Princely apparel, and put off his ſhoos, and ſtockings. This is verily believ'd by many Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts, and yet <hi>Gretſer</hi> ſaith, that the Grecians, <hi>Zonoras, Cedrenus,</hi> and the like, write nothing of it, yet profeſſeth withal he likes it never the worſe for their ſilence; for they (as he farther obſerves) omitted many other material truths whereof no man of reaſon will ever call them in queſtion; and though <hi>Hermannus Contractus, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radus, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſpergenſis Abbas,</hi> and others ſpeak nothing of this <hi>Joane,</hi> we muſt not therefore conclude that there was never ſuch a <hi>Woman</hi> once a <hi>Pope.</hi> Do arguments taken from authority of few men hold nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively? Is it a good Argument, St. <hi>Paul,</hi> St. <hi>Luke,</hi> and <hi>Seneca</hi> do not ſay that St. <hi>Peter</hi> was at <hi>Rome?
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:58390:39"/>Ergo</hi> St. <hi>Peter</hi> was not at <hi>Rome.</hi> I anſwer with<note n="z" place="margin">Lib. de Rom. pontif. cap. <hi>8</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bellarmin, negative arguments are nothing worth;</hi> for it follows not that St. <hi>Peter</hi> was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver at <hi>Rome,</hi> becauſe St. <hi>Luke,</hi> St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Seneca</hi> do not report that he was ever there: for theſe three were not bound to report all that was true. Certainly (ſaith one) <hi>magis credi debet tribus teſtibus affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantibus quam infinitis nihil dicen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus; a man ſhould rather believe t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ee witneſſes ſpeaking to a cauſe, than infinite who ſpeak neither</hi> pro <hi>nor</hi> con. Again, <hi>Denis Biſhop of Athens</hi> was afterwards <hi>Biſhop of Paris,</hi> though <hi>Ado Biſhop of Triers</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> and <hi>Suidas,</hi> a Greek Author, make no mention of his removal to another Biſhoprick. <hi>Lipomannus</hi> reſolves upon <hi>Metaphraſtes</hi> and one <hi>Michael Syngelus</hi> in theſe words, that <hi>Denis</hi> was Biſhop of <hi>Paris,</hi> though <hi>Ado,</hi> and <hi>Suidas</hi> ſay nothing of it. Why then though theſe and many more
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:58390:40"/>ſay nothing of <hi>Pope Joan,</hi> might there not be ſuch a <hi>Pope,</hi> ſince as many, and as learned as they, do place her in the number of <hi>Popes.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Proligom. <hi>6</hi> in Evangelia.</note> 
               <hi>Salmeron</hi> a learned Jeſuit ſaith thus, <hi>Ea lex apud Hiſtorigraphos obſervatur, ut quando unus ex duobus hiſtoricis aliquid affirmat quod alius ſupprimit, non deroget affirmanti qui tacet; That when one Hiſtorian re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports what another paſſeth by, the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſilence doth not prejudice the truth of the others relation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs there is not a word of her in all thoſe ſix or ſeven <hi>Tables</hi> which are in the <hi>Vatican;</hi> yet ſuppoſe theſe <hi>Tables</hi> be of greateſt eſtimation, yet ſhall we conclude that he that is as Pope regiſtred therein was a Pope; I know not how ſafely we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it, ſince <hi>Baronius</hi> condemns ſuch for ſilly credulous people, who believe reports the rather becauſe they are to be found in
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:58390:40"/>Books belonging to the <hi>Popes Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brary.</hi> Beſides <hi>Leo</hi> the 8 is regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred in the <hi>Catalogue of Popes,</hi> and in ſome of thoſe ſeven <hi>Tables,</hi> if not in them all, yet<note n="b" place="margin">Annalium. tom. <hi>10.</hi> ad annum. <hi>964.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Baronius,</hi> and his followers conclude him an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truder, and Uſurper, and did not in the leaſt deſerve that glorious Title of a <hi>Pope.</hi> Now if this be no good argument <hi>Leo</hi> the 8 is numbred among the <hi>Popes</hi> in ſeven <hi>Tables,</hi> in the <hi>Popes Library,</hi> or in ſeven as authentical, <hi>Ergo Leo the</hi> 8 was a <hi>Pope;</hi> from hence may be ſaid, that <hi>Joan</hi> the <hi>Woman Pope</hi> is not numbred amongſt the <hi>Popes</hi> in thoſe ſeven <hi>Tables</hi> in the <hi>Popes Library: Ergo</hi> there was no ſuch <hi>Joan,</hi> a <hi>Woman Pope.</hi> But con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider if ſeven <hi>Tables</hi> ſpeaking for a <hi>Pope</hi> do not convince the being of ſuch a <hi>Pope,</hi> why ſhould their ſilence argue the contrary? might there not be as well, one left out that was a <hi>Pope,</hi> as <hi>commemorize</hi>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:58390:41"/>one that never was? Beſides, there are ſeveral reaſons why it was requiſit ſhe ſhould be left out, either for her Sex ſake, being a Woman, and very ſalacious, or elſe ſhe would never have rambled over ſeveral Countries with a man, who undoubtedly in their travels lay together; or elſe in regard of the foulneſs of the fact, which as it brands her Memory with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual infamy, ſo it cannot but prove a great blot in the Papal Eſcutcheon.</p>
            <p>This omiſſion of her name need not ſeem ſtrange, if you will but obſerve, that other <hi>Popes,</hi> upon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther occaſions, have been paſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in ſilence by ſeveral Writers as no <hi>Popes;</hi> as for example; <hi>Faelix the</hi> 2. was both <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Martyr</hi> (as<note n="c" place="margin">Lib. <hi>4.</hi> de Roman. Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tif. cap <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bellarmin</hi> affirmeth) and he ſate as <hi>Pope</hi> one year, four months, and two days, as you may read in<note n="d" place="margin">Invita Fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licis.</note> 
               <hi>Platina:</hi> yet by<note n="e" place="margin">Chronol. lib. <hi>3.</hi> ad annum. <hi>368.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Genebrards</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:58390:41"/>
               <hi>Marcellinus</hi> omits to ſpeak of him, in his <hi>Chronicle,</hi> becauſe he was ſuſpected of hereſy; and for the ſame, or ſuch like cauſe St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and <hi>Optatus,</hi> mention him not among the <hi>Popes</hi> in their <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morials.</hi> That one <hi>Cyriacus</hi> was <hi>Pope</hi> is acknowledged by divers, yet it is rare to find him in any <hi>Clatalogue of Popes</hi> of whom <hi>Johannes de Pariſiis,</hi> a great Papiſt, in his Treatiſe <hi>de poteſtate regia &amp; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pali,</hi> writes thus; <hi>Iſte Cyriacus in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogo Paparum non annumeratur, quia credebant ipſum non propter devotio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ſed propter oblectamentum Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginum dimiſiſſe Epiſcopatum.</hi> Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riacus <hi>is not in the Catalogue of Popes, becauſe it was thought he left the Popedom not for Devotion but for the ſake of Wenching. Damaſus</hi> the ſecond hath his name regiſtred in many<note n="f" place="margin">Platina in vita Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſi <hi>2.</hi> Polo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s in Chronic. circa an. <hi>1040.</hi>
               </note> Popiſh Chronicles in the throng of <hi>Popes;</hi> yet there are<note n="g" place="margin">Platina l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> citato.</note> many on the otherſide who let him
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:58390:42"/>go for a <hi>Scabby ſheep.</hi> Thus <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tina, cenſent nonnulli hunc inter Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifices nequaquam numerandum eſſe; ſome judge this fellow no ways fit to be regiſtred among the Popes;</hi> and in like manner they deal with many others.</p>
            <p>But<note n="h" place="margin">Florimondus Cap. <hi>22.</hi> p. <hi>190.</hi>
               </note> ſome may ſay if <hi>Pope Joan</hi> was omitted in the regiſters of ſome for the filthineſs of her fact, why was that <hi>Cloſe-ſtool</hi> reſerved, and that Monument of hers erected where ſhe was publickly deliver'd; for the <hi>Stool,</hi> and the <hi>Image</hi> were as like to continue the memory of her, as any record in writing. To this I anſwer may not ſome be of one opinion, ſome of another? May not ſome think good to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the memory of that which others for ſhame would willingly have forgoten? Hence not ſome Papiſts in <hi>France</hi> denied that <hi>John Chaſtel</hi> was taught by the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> to murther <hi>Henry the fourth of France,</hi>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:58390:42"/>becauſe they were loath the <hi>Jeſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>its</hi> ſhould ſeem odious? and yet did not others contribute their aſſiſtance in the erection of a ſtony Pillar near the Kings Palace, whereby ſo much was notified; If any man ſhould affirm that the ſame man who omited <hi>Pope Joan</hi> for the filthineſs of her fact, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected ſuch a Monument for her in one of the High-ſtreets in <hi>Rome,</hi> and proſcribed ſuch a <hi>Stool</hi> to be kept for that purpoſe I know not how he could free himſelf from contradiction.</p>
            <p>For further Proof whereof I think this worth the conſideration, that when <hi>Paul the Third</hi> moved with the Spirit of God (as<note n="i" place="margin">In his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joinder to Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop Jewel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Maſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> p. <hi>177.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> ſaith) and deſirous to reform the Church gave charge to the moſt Learned, Wiſe, Pious, and Zealous men he knew, <hi>viz.</hi> four Cardinals, three Biſhops, and two others to enquire and ſearch
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:58390:43"/>out what abuſes and diſorders were in the Church, and eſpecially in the Roman Court; which they did accordingly, and preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him a Libel conteining the ſum of all their proceedings. Some thought their Labours merited Regiſtring; others thought them fitter to be committed to the fire, which appears by this, that the Libel is Printed in <hi>Crabbs</hi> edition of the Council, anno 1551, and yet inſerted in the <hi>Index librorum prohibitorum</hi> by <hi>Paul the fourth,</hi> (one of thoſe four Cardinals that exhibited it to <hi>Paul the third</hi>) and left out of <hi>Dominicus Nicolinus</hi> his Edition of the Councils at <hi>Venice auſpiciis Sixti Quinti,</hi> in the year 1585. and out of <hi>Severinus Bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> his Edition at <hi>Colen</hi> 1606.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Bell. lib. <hi>3.</hi> de Rom. Pont. cap. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note>But ſay the Papiſts again, grant that <hi>Pope Joan</hi> ſhould be omitted for the filthineſs of her fact, yet ſhould there have been mention
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:58390:43"/>made of the vacancy of the See for that time ſhe was <hi>Pope,</hi> elſe there will bee a manifeſt errour in Chronology.</p>
            <p>A foul errour indeed to miſs two years in reckoning; there may be fouler than this, and yet the matter ſalved well enough. For <hi>Onuphrius</hi> reckons 230. <hi>Popes</hi> to <hi>Gregory the</hi> 13, and <hi>Genebrard</hi> and <hi>Maſſonus</hi> 234. whereas <hi>Plati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> accounts 235; for he reckons to <hi>Ziſtus the fourth,</hi> with whom he ends, 221 <hi>Popes:</hi> afer whom, to <hi>Gregory</hi> the 13, every one reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons 14,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>l</hi> Anaſtaſ. de Vita Evariſt.</note> which compleats the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of 235: yet <hi>Verſteganus,</hi> in his Table printed at <hi>Antwerp</hi> 1590, numbers no more than 231. Moreover do not ſeveral Chrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies written by <hi>k</hi> Romaniſts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, that <hi>Evariſtus</hi> ſate 13 years, whereas others ſay, he ſate but<note n="m" place="margin">Baron, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. tom. <hi>2.</hi> ad annum. <hi>121.</hi> Num. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> nine years? do not<note n="n" place="margin">Baron. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. tom. <hi>2.</hi> ad Anno <hi>172.</hi> Num. <hi>21..</hi>
               </note> ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſay that <hi>Denis</hi> ſate;<note n="o" place="margin">Annaſtas. de vita Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſii<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> others that he
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:58390:44"/>ſate but two years. I think theſe differences, and ſuch as theſe are argue manifeſt errours in their Chronologies; If no further incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies follow upon <hi>Pope Joans</hi> omiſſion, than a manifeſt errour in Chronology, for that ſpace ſhe lived, we may well enough believe that ſome omitted her, not becauſe there was no ſuch Perſon, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were aſhamed of her; for two years, and odd months break no ſquare in their Chrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies, no more than a miſtake of two inches in a foot with a bungle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Carpenter.</p>
            <p>I, but ſays <hi>Florimondus, no man ever writ of her till four hundred years after her death; and is it poſſible that all writers ſhould ſo conſpire together, that the truth thereof could never be certainly known, till ſo long a time after the expiration of her Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:58390:44"/>
            <p>I have already proved by the books that are yet extant, that this ſtory was ſooner diſcover'd. But ſuppoſe we had no Author who lived within 400. years of <hi>Pope Joane</hi> to produce for proof, muſt therefore the ſtory be rejected? Do not the Papiſts recommend, as truths, many ſtories, for which they can bring no teſtimony out of any Writer who lived within 400. years after?<note n="p" place="margin">Bell. lib. <hi>2.</hi> de Image cap. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> They tell us of an Image of Chriſt which was made by <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> who came to our Saviour by night for fear of the <hi>Jews;</hi> and of it runs a report of ſtrange <hi>Miracles</hi> it effects: yet are not able to name the man who wrote of this 600. years after <hi>Nicodemus.</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Bel. loco ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tato &amp; Gret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer de Cruce lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> They tell us that St. <hi>Luke</hi> drew certain pictures of the <hi>Virgin Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> but<note n="r" place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectan.</note> 
               <hi>Theodorus Lector</hi> is the firſt man that makes this report, and he lived at leaſt 500. years after. Not to trouble you with many more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:58390:45"/>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Baron An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Tom. <hi>1.</hi> ad An Chriſti. <hi>31.</hi> Nu. <hi>61.</hi>
               </note> they write, that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour wiping his face with a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerchief, imprinted his own Effigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es therein, and ſent it to <hi>Agbarus</hi> for a token; but for proof hereof, there is no Author to be produced, but one<note n="t" place="margin">Baron. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. Tom. <hi>8.</hi> ad An. <hi>594.</hi> Nu. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Evagrius,</hi> who lived 600. years after Chriſt. That the <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Mary</hi> made that coat of our Saviours which was without ſeam the<note n="u" place="margin">Annotat. in Joh. <hi>19.23.</hi> in Margine.</note> 
               <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> peremptorily affirm, and<note n="x" place="margin">Ludolphus de vita Jeſu. part. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>63.</hi> p. <hi>221.</hi> Coloſs. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> others of the like faction add, that as our Saviour grew in height, and breadth, ſo the Coat on his back grew in like manner. I cannot read any Author they have produced that writeth hereof for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 400 years ſince.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But how comes it about that</hi> Pope Joan <hi>ſhould be called John, as ſhe was ſuppoſed a man after her election, ſince Popes upon their election do now change their names from a laudible cuſtom</hi> (ſaith <hi>Florimondus</hi>) <hi>that</hi> Sergius (<hi>a few years before Pope</hi> Joan)
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:58390:45"/>
               <hi>introduced, which was that the Pope elect ſhould not ſtep out of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clave till he had changed his proper name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is confeſt, that<note n="y" place="margin">Faſcic. Temp. ad An. <hi>844.</hi> Pol. Virg. de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Invent. Stella de vitis Pont. in Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> ſome ſay that, becauſe <hi>Sergius</hi> had a filthy beaſtly name before his election, <hi>viz Swines-ſnout,</hi> he changed it after his election; but they are miſtaken who ſay <hi>Sergius the</hi> 2 changed his proper name, for <hi>ex paterno nomine a principio Sergius eſt appellatus;</hi> from his birth he was called <hi>Sergius</hi> after the name of his father, ſo writes <hi>Baronius</hi> in his <hi>Annals</hi> Tome the tenth, to the year 844. The firſt who changed his name was <hi>Sergius the third,</hi> and yet not for the filthineſs of his name, but in reverence to St. <hi>Peter. Cum enim ille Petrus vocaretur indignum ſe putavit vocari eodem nomine, quo Chriſtus primum ej<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s ſedis Pontificem Principem Apoſtolorum ex</hi> Simone Petrum <hi>nominaverat: for his name
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:58390:46"/>being</hi> Peter, <hi>he thought it not fit, to be called by that name whereby Chriſt called the firſt Biſhop of that See, even the Prince of the Apoſtles, whoſe name be changed from Simon to</hi> Peter, as may be further read in that <hi>Learned Cardinal, Caeſar Baronius.</hi> Notwithſtanding this poſitive aſſertion, of <hi>Baronius,</hi> I ſee this great Scholar, as well as other Bug-bears of wit, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy may not only groſly mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, but down right contradict themſelves; for (ſaith he) in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother place, <hi>Tom.</hi> 10. <hi>Annal. ad Ann.</hi> 955. <hi>Nu.</hi> 4. ſpeaking <hi>of</hi> John <hi>the twelfth. Hic revera pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus inventus qui mutavit ſibi nomen, ut qui ex Octaviano vocari voluerit Johannes pro mutata non exuta tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nide:</hi> 
               <q>This, in truth is the firſt who changed his name, who of <hi>Octavian</hi> would needs be called <hi>John;</hi> not that he meant to leave his tyranny, but to uſe it in another
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:58390:46"/>kind; for he, who was called by his Father <hi>Octavian,</hi> in reſpect of his temporal authority in the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, would now in reſpect of his ſpiritual, be called <hi>John:</hi> either becauſe his Uncle <hi>John</hi> the 11. was called ſo, or for that he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to hear well at leaſt for his nameſake, whilſt in clawing, and fawning acclamations the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple baſely applyed unto him that good ſpeech, <hi>there was a man that was ſent from God whoſe name was John.</hi>
               </q> Thus <hi>Baronius;</hi> and now <hi>Florimondus</hi> not knowing almoſt what to ſay, asks the queſtion, <hi>who was Pope</hi> Joans <hi>Father, quinam hujus Pſeudopontificis pater;</hi> if ſhe had a Father, certainly he would have been mention'd in Hiſtory, as well as the Father of <hi>Linus, Clerus, Clemens,</hi> and of all the reſt of Popes, in anſwer hereunto, that the Hiſtories expreſly ſet down the Fathers of all the reſt of
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:58390:47"/>the Popes is falſe. For by Hiſtory no man knows of what parentage<note n="z" place="margin">Anaſtaſ. de vit. Pont. in vita Higini.</note> 
               <hi>Higinus</hi> was; <hi>Higini genealogia non invenitur,</hi> neither can we find out the Anceſtors of <hi>Pope Denis;</hi> as <hi>Anaſtaſius,</hi> afore quoted, doth acknowledge; <hi>Dioniſii generatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem invenire non potuimus;</hi> And it is unknown of what Sir-name or Country <hi>John</hi> the 19. was:<note n="a" place="margin">Stella de vitis Pant. in vita Johan. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Johan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis</hi> 19, <hi>cognomen et patria ignoratur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Hiſtories it is expreſly written, that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban the fourth</hi> was begotten by a Cobler,<note n="b" place="margin">Onuph. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not. in Plat. in vita <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbani. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ex patre Sutore ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teramentario;</hi> that <hi>John the two and twentieth</hi> was the Son of a Botcher,<note n="c" place="margin">Longius in Chron. ad An. <hi>1316.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Filius <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eteramentarii, reſarcitoris ſcilicet ſotelarium:</hi> That <hi>Benedict</hi> the eleventh was the Son of a poor Laundreſs;<note n="d" place="margin">ibid.</note> 
               <hi>Filius Lotricis pauperculae:</hi> that <hi>Benedict the twelfth</hi> was the Son of a Milner <hi>Molitoris filius;</hi> That <hi>Sixtus the fourth</hi> was the Son of a Mariner,<note n="e" place="margin">Papyr. Maſſ. de urbis Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cop. lib. <hi>6.</hi> in Sixto <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>patre ortus qui ſemper nauticam exercuit;</hi> that
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:58390:47"/>
               <hi>Adrian the ſixth</hi> was the Son of a Cloath-worker, or as ſome ſay a Brewer: That<note n="f" place="margin">Cicarellus in Vita Sixti <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sixtus Quintus</hi> was the Son of a Swin-heard, but what the names of theſe mens Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were, that is not expreſly written.<note n="g" place="margin">Papyr. Maſ. de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbis Epiſ. lib. <hi>6.</hi> in Alex. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Alexander the fifth</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed; <hi>Se nec parentes, nec fratres, nec aliquem ex agnatis, cognatiſque ſuis unquam vidiſſe:</hi> That he never ſaw either his Father, or Mother, or Brother, or any of his kindred; who then can tell his Fathers name?</p>
            <p>Beating ſome of the Romaniſts from this idle interrogatory, they fly to this; either this <hi>Pope Joan</hi> was young, or old when ſhe was choſen. If ſhe was young, it was contrary to cuſtom to admit of any ſuch election; as may appear by the great number of Popes that lived in the dignity above the number of Emperours that ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded often in their youth. But if ſhe were old when ſhe was cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:58390:48"/>then how did ſhe bear a Child publickly in proceſſion? the ground work of this argument, that <hi>Pope Joan</hi> was either young, or old, may be eaſily deſtroyed thus; if we conſider that learned men di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide the whole courſe of mans life not into youth and old age; but into <hi>Pueritiam, pubertatem; adole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcentiam, juventutem conſtantem me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diumve &amp; ſenectutem.</hi> Now mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle age is from 35. to 49. wherof ſhe might have been, and ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther old, nor young; for <hi>Leo the</hi> 10 was choſen Pope at 38 years of age, being not 46 years old when he died, and yet he ſate as <hi>Pope</hi> 8 years, 8 months, and 20 days; and <hi>Gregory the</hi> 11. was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 35 years old when he was choſen, as<note n="h" place="margin">Niem <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis Tract. <hi>5.</hi> cap <hi>39.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Theodoricus de Niem,</hi> and <hi>Maſſonus</hi> teſtify, beſides, ſhe might have been choſen young for any Popiſh cuſtom there is to the contrary. For<note n="i" place="margin">Maſſon. de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbis Epiſcop. in Boniface <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Boniface the</hi> 9 at
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:58390:48"/>the age of 34 was choſen Pope; and <hi>Innocent</hi> the 3 was but 30. I know not but our <hi>Joan</hi> might have been one of the youths of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh; For not to ſpeak of the <hi>Boy Pope</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Glab. Radul. hiſt. lib. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Benedict the</hi> 9. who was choſen Pope about twelf years old, one, who at that age better underſtood a Gig, and Bowling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtones, than the diſciplin of the Church, I ſay not to reflect on him particularly,<note n="l" place="margin">Paulus Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius in Chron, Citizenſe ad An. <hi>1389.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>John</hi> 13 <hi>alias</hi> 12 <hi>In juvenili &amp; florida aetate creatur Pontifex,</hi> He was conſtituted Pope when he was in his youth and flouriſhing condition; that is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the 18 year of his age, as<note n="m" place="margin">Annal. Tom. <hi>10.</hi> ad anno <hi>955.</hi> num. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Baronius</hi> gathereth by circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances.</p>
            <p>But why might ſhe not have been old, ſince we read, and have known experimentally that old women have born children. <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the Emperour</hi> begat <hi>Frederick the</hi> 2 on a Wife who was fifty
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:58390:49"/>years old, ſo ſaith <hi>Maſſonus:</hi> and <hi>Machutus</hi> the Biſhop (ſaith <hi>Petrus de Natalibus</hi>) was born when his Mother was above threeſcore: and ſaith <hi>Franſciſcus Junius</hi> in his annotations on <hi>Ruth; Hic in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latinatu ante annos aliquot vidi meis occulis &amp; vocatus interfui par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus cujuſdem foeminae amplius annos</hi> 56 <hi>natae, quae binos mores enixa eſt eodem partu:</hi> A few years ſince I was intreated to ſee a woman a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 59 years old, who was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verd of two Boys at a Birth; why may not then <hi>Pope Joan</hi> (though fifty) be deliver'd of a Son.</p>
            <p>Again let us conſider, that the multitude of Popes above the Emperours was not by reaſon of their age, but by other accidents. In the firſt 300 years while the Popes were Generally good, they were cut off by Martyrdom, for though it be not true (as <hi>Onuphri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> very well obſerves) that all the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:58390:49"/>Popes from St. <hi>Peters</hi> time to <hi>Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſter</hi> were <hi>Martyrs</hi> (which is confidently avouched by ſome of the Romiſh party) yet I grant it for a truth, that moſt of them were ſo. Now in ſucceeding times their number grew the greater by their poiſoning and murdering one another. Diligently peruſe the Hiſtory of their Lives, and you ſhall find that of forty Popes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed, there was not one ſate a full year:<note n="n" place="margin">Faſcic. Temp. ad an. <hi>904.</hi>
               </note> you ſhall find that in a little more than nine years, there were nine ſeveral Popes: you ſhall find that one man, in 13 years, poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned ſix Popes: Laſtly you ſhall find, that God in his juſtice did cut them off for their wicked and abominable lewd Lives and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Liberius</hi> ſate about ſome ſix years, ſaith <hi>Cardinal</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Sum. de Eccleſ. lib. <hi>4.</hi> part. <hi>1.</hi> c <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Turrecrema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> and then died an evil Death, <hi>mala morte precibus Sanctorum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinctus
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:58390:50"/>eſt;</hi> he died not for age, but with curſing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anaſtaſius</hi> the ſecond ſate not two years but God ſtruck him ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly for his wickedneſs, and he died miſerably: for he died as ſome ſay, as <hi>Arius</hi> the Arch-here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, of which opinion is<note n="p" place="margin">Platina in vita Anaſtaſii <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Platina</hi> and<note n="q" place="margin">Stella de Vit. Pont. ad annum <hi>498.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Stella,</hi> who ſay, <hi>Sunt qui ſcribunt eum in Latrinam effudiſſe inteſtina dum neceſſitati naturae ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperat;</hi> In a houſe of office he evacuated his guts with his excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clement</hi> the ſecond continued in the Papacy but nine months, and died not of old age but poyſon: ſo ſays <hi>Genebrard</hi> and <hi>Aeneas Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Damaſus</hi> the ſecond, who had a hand in poyſoning this <hi>Clement,</hi> kept the Popedom but 23 days, not that he died of old age, but by the juſt judgment of God, that he might be an example to others
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:58390:50"/>(as <hi>Platina</hi> obſerves) who climb to that dignity by unjuſt and indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect means, to which they ſhould aſcend by virtue, and true me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Benedict</hi> the ſixth lived Pope no longer than a year and a half, and then died in a Goal by ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, or famine, as<note n="r" place="margin">Annal. Tom. <hi>10.</hi> ad anno <hi>974.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Baronius</hi> is of opinion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Victor</hi> the third was no longer Pope but one year, and four months and died by Poyſon, ſo ſays <hi>Platina, Genebrard, Charanza,</hi> and <hi>Polonus;</hi> by the ſame means (as is ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) died <hi>Pius</hi> the third.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John</hi> the thirteenth (<hi>alias</hi> twelve) was ſlain in the very act of adultery, whether thruſt through by one that ſaw him in that beaſtly poſture (as <hi>Platina</hi> believes) or murdred by the Devil (as <hi>Luitprandus</hi> ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins) Hiſtorians agree not in; but<note n="ſ" place="margin">Turrecrema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ſum. de Eccleſ. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>103.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Turrecremata,</hi> a <hi>Cardinal,</hi> takes that as more likely, that is moſt
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:58390:51"/>dreadful: for becauſe (ſaith he) the Life of <hi>Pope John</hi> was deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and intolerable offenſive to the Chriſtian People, therefore Chriſt himſelf pronounced againſt him ſentence of condemnation: for, whilſt he was abuſing, and vitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a certain mans Wife, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil ſtruck him ſuddainly into the temple of his head, and he died as ſuddainly without repentance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Boniface</hi> the ſeventh ſate but ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven months, and a few days, and then the Beaſt dyed, ſaith<note n="t" place="margin">Metrop. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Kran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Marcellus</hi> the Second lived but 22 days in the Papacy, not that he was very aged when he died (for he was but 55 years old) but for that he was poyſoned, and which is ſtrange, it is obſerved, that he was poyſoned, becauſe ſome thought he would prove an honeſt Pope. <hi>Obiit die</hi> 22, <hi>non ſine veneni ſuſpitione, quod nimium rectius qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſdam
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:58390:51"/>videretur,</hi> ſaith<note n="u" place="margin">Chron. lib. <hi>4.</hi> ad annum <hi>1555.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brard.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>Sixtus Quintus,</hi> after the ſixth year of his Reign was fetcht away by the Devil, by whoſe help he came to that place,<note n="x" place="margin">In his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarat. made at Vendome Jan. <hi>28. 1601.</hi>
               </note> Sr. <hi>Francis Breton,</hi> a Monk of the order of the <hi>Celeſtines,</hi> proteſted that a <hi>Prior of St Benets</hi> order aſſured him at <hi>Rome</hi> and the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> at <hi>Italy</hi> ſeem to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve no leſs by their own reports. To conclude, it is the confeſſion of many Pontificial Writers, that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Popes were ſhort liv'd, becauſe God ſaw they proved Monſters in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of pious men, and became a ſhame, and ſcandal to the true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; wherefore God in his ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice ſnatcht them off from the face of the Earth. Thus this argument of years hath its anſwer.</p>
            <p>Another objection they alledg; that it is a moſt unlikely thing that the whole Roman Clergy would chuſe a Pope without a beard, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:58390:52"/>if all the Clergy in thoſe days, (as ſome write) were ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. For men by ſhaving may make themſelves look like wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and women by often ſhaving may make them ſelves look like men,<note n="y" place="margin">Pro barbis Sacerdotum, fol. <hi>21.</hi> ad Card. Medicen Lond. Anno <hi>1533.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Johannes Pierius Valerianus</hi> a learned man, imputes the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of the choice of <hi>Pope Joan</hi> to this, that the Clergy in thoſe days were generally ſhaven: for by the means of ſhaving (ſaith he) the people were ſo diſguiſed, that men and women were in a manner un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſtinguiſhable, and by this it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that a woman was choſen Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> to the perpetual ſhame, and infamy of that ſacred dignity; of the ſame opinion is<note n="z" place="margin">Lib. <hi>5.</hi> de Rebus Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cicis.</note> 
               <hi>Chalcocondilas.</hi> Thus then ſince it was an ordinary thing for the Clergy to be ſhaven, why ſhould they diſlike her the more for want of a beard.</p>
            <pb n="97" facs="tcp:58390:52"/>
            <p>But ſome may ſay, that it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſtrange, that in all that time, neither voice, countenance, not actions ſhould not diſcover her. To this I anſwer, that if there be truth in Popiſh Writers; diverſe Women have lived longer among Men in Mens apparel unknown, than <hi>Dame Joan</hi> lived in the Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. For <hi>Marina</hi> (as <hi>i Textor</hi> reports) lived all her Life among <hi>Monks</hi> in a Maſculine habit, and none knew any thing to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, but that ſhe was a <hi>Monk</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Pet. de Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal. in Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. ſanc. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Euphroſina</hi> lived thirty ſix years among <hi>Monks,</hi> and was reputed for a <hi>Monk;</hi> ſo did <hi>Eugenia, Pela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia,</hi> and <hi>Margareta,</hi> and their Sex the while was unſuſpected. In our late Civil Wars, I knew a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that was ſixteen years a Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, at length, being tired with that ſtarving kind of Life, return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to her relations, and reaſſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her priſtin proper habiliments,<note n="a" place="margin">Text. in Officina Tit. Mul. hab. vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril. ment.</note>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:58390:53"/>was in a little time Married, and had ſeveral Children afterwards.</p>
            <p>The Romaniſts, to make this ſtory the more fabulous, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable, do ſay, that certainly this <hi>Woman Pope</hi> (had there been any ſuch Perſon) would not have been guilty of ſo much indiſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (eſpecially having the repute of ſo much Wit, and Scholarſhip) as to go abroad in publick, being ſo near her time, and venture to go in <hi>Proceſſion,</hi> where ſhe muſt conſequently have the eyes of many thouſands fixt upon her, whereby, if no other accident ſhould happen, ſhe runs the hazard of a diſcovery. To this I anſwer, that the time of Child-birth is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain, for commonly women go ten months, yet ſometimes they come ſooner, at nine, eight, yea, and at ſeven months, as<note n="c" place="margin">Levin. Lemnius de occult. Nat. miraculis lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap <hi>22.</hi> &amp; <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans have obſerved. Honeſter wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men than <hi>Pope Joan</hi> have fallen in
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:58390:53"/>Travail upon the high-way; nay in the ſtreet, their unexpected pangs have come ſo faſt upon them that they have been forced to take ſanctuary at the next houſe they could come at, and make bold with a ſtranger in a mean habitation, rather than be delivered in the ſtreet; ſuitable to this is an obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of <hi>Theophilact; novit mulier quod pariet, quando vero non novit: nam non paucae</hi> 8 <hi>menſe pepererunt, etiam in itinere, nihil praeſcientes;</hi> (ſays he) a woman knows ſhe ſhall be deliver'd, but the time when, ſhe knows not: for diverſe have been deliver'd in their eight month, as they have been on a journey, not imagining they were ſo near their reckoning. Thus may this poor Gentlewoman, <hi>Pope Joan</hi> be miſtaken, and the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe this was her firſt that ſhe was deliver'd of, as ſhe went to St. <hi>John Laterans,</hi> for we
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:58390:54"/>do not read, that ſhe had a Baſtard before ſhe was <hi>Pope,</hi> not, but that we may believe it upon good grounds, that her fellow Traveller, or Gallant was not wanting in his indeavours to give her that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſatisfaction ſhe deſired; and it may be ſhe proved upon it too, but had an Art, which the Devil taught her, to carry it off again by medecine, a practice of late too much uſed by ſome inſatiate <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalinas</hi> of this Kingdom: whether ſhe uſed it or not, we know no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proof but bare conjecture, but certain it is, ſhe was deliver'd of a Son in the open ſtreet, and both expired immediately there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, who were buried together without any ſolemnity, and though ſhe had born the greateſt offices belonging to the <hi>Romiſh Church,</hi> yet ſhe was interr'd without the common ceremonies of Burial.</p>
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:58390:54"/>
            <p>The Sacred Scriptures do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form us, that God in his juſtice doth uſe to ſerve the greateſt Princes ſo, who diſhonour him. Do we not read that <hi>Jehoiachim King of Judah</hi> was to be buried as an Aſs was buried, <hi>&amp;c. Jerem.</hi> 22.18, 19. and we read in Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, that many Popes have had as ſmall ſolemnities. <hi>Boniface the</hi> 7. (ſaith<note n="d" place="margin">Annal. Tom. <hi>10.</hi> ad An. <hi>985.</hi> è veterê Pontif. vati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cano codice.</note> 
               <hi>Baronius</hi>) who ſate af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>John the</hi> 15, in four months dyed a ſuddain death, and was ſo hateful to his own followers, that after his death they ſhowed their deteſtation of him, by revenging themſelves with Blows on his ſenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Carkaſs, whilſt others with ſwords ran him through, and through; after this they draged him by the feet ſtark naked, till they came to the field which is near the place where <hi>Conſtantines</hi> Horſe ſtands, there they threw him from them, and ſo left him.
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:58390:55"/>
               <hi>Debora Rebecca's Nurſe,</hi> was buried under an Oak and <hi>Rachel Jacobs Wife,</hi> (a far honeſter woman than <hi>Pope Joan</hi>) was buried in the way to <hi>Ephrath.</hi> This woman Pope could not have a burial too bad for her; a fact ſo extraordinary, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved an extraordinary uſage, wherefore <hi>Papyrius Maſſonus</hi> que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions the truth of this ſtory, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe was not ſhameful enough handled; for (ſaith he) had there been any ſuch Pope, the Romans could have done no leſs in equity, than after Death, to have hanged her up in chains. But how comes it about, if ſhe was deliver'd of a Boy, that ſhe dyed inſtantly? <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimondus</hi> accounts this, as one of the adſurdities which attend this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>able, <hi>Maſculum pepererat</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>quid igitur mortem repentinam attu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit?</hi> If a Woman be once deliver'd of the fruit of her Womb, there is no danger of Death in his opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:58390:55"/>In the firſt place, ſhe did not die inſtantly, though ſuddainly, for ſhe was deliver'd of a Boy before her death, in the next place, I would fain know, whether it is not common for women to dye in Child-bed, as well as in Child-birth. <hi>Rachel</hi> was delivered of her Son <hi>Benjamin,</hi> and yet died ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after, <hi>Gen.</hi> 35, 17.18. <hi>Phineas</hi> wife was deliver'd of her Son <hi>Icho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bod,</hi> and yet dyed preſently after. And if they dyed ſo, why not <hi>Pope Joan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I but can ſhe be ſaid to have gon from the Palace of St. <hi>Peter</hi> to St. <hi>John Lateran,</hi> whereas the Popes laid not then in the <hi>Vatican,</hi> but at St <hi>John Lateran it ſelf,</hi> this<note n="e" place="margin">Bellar. de Rom. Pontif. cap. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bellarmin,</hi> and others do object; and <hi>Platina</hi> (ſays ſome) doth ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtify, that the Popes lay not in the <hi>Vatican</hi> till the year 1350, which was in the time of <hi>Boniface</hi> the Ninth.</p>
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:58390:56"/>
            <p>This is a great miſtake, for <hi>Boniface</hi> the Ninth lived in the year 1390, not 1350, the like miſtake there is in fathering ſuch a fancy upon<note n="f" place="margin">In Vita Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifac.</note> 
               <hi>Platina.</hi> For <hi>Platina</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports only, that the <hi>Vatican</hi> was repair'd by <hi>Boniface</hi> the Ninth; he ſaith not it was firſt inhabited by him, though if he had, the Pope might have gone to ſee the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teran;</hi> for he had more than one houſe to ſolace himſelf, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodate his retinue in beſides the <hi>Lateran.</hi> He dwelt not always in that,<note n="g" place="margin">De vitis Pontif. in vita Gregorii.</note> for <hi>Gregory</hi> the Fourth, built two ſtately Fabricks for the Popes uſe, as <hi>Anaſtaſius</hi> teſtifies: and <hi>Leo</hi> the Third, (as you may read in the ſame Author) built another no leſs glorious, near to St. <hi>Peters</hi> Church, which ſtands in the <hi>Vatican,</hi> wherein <hi>Leo</hi> the Fourth gave entertainment to <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dovike</hi> the Emperour. Beſides, Hiſtory doth not mention that ſhe
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:58390:56"/>went from St. <hi>Peters</hi> Palace to the Palace of the <hi>Lateran,</hi> but from St. <hi>Peters</hi> Church to the <hi>Lateran</hi> Church, and yet dwell in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace by the <hi>Lateran;</hi> for Popes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin not their Proceſſion from the next Church adjoyning to them. <hi>Leo</hi> the Third appointed to go in Proceſſion three ſeveral days be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Aſcenſion day; and he began the firſt day at one of St. <hi>Maries</hi> Churches, and ended at St. <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours</hi> Church: the ſecond day he began at St. <hi>Sabina</hi> the Martyrs Church, and ended at St. <hi>Pauls:</hi> and the third day he began at St. <hi>Croſſes</hi> Church in <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and ended at St. <hi>Laurences</hi> without the Walls; ſo that this objection I conceive is fully anſwered, and I ſhall endeavour to do the like to ſeveral others; and firſt, the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts do cavil much about her different names before her Papacy; ſome ſay ſhe was called <hi>Agnes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>h</hi> Platina in vita Leonis.</note>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:58390:57"/>ſome <hi>Gilbert,</hi> ſome <hi>Iſabel,</hi> ſome <hi>Margaret,</hi> ſome <hi>Tutta,</hi> or <hi>Jutta,</hi> and others <hi>Dorothie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is a meer Forgery, for I cannot Read in any Antient Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, that ſhe was called by any of theſe Names; in ſome of later time I find ſome difference, one calling her <hi>Gilbert,</hi> and another <hi>Agnes,</hi> but of all thoſe whom I have here inſerted, to aſſert the truth, and give in evidence againſt her, there is not above one or two, who either before or after her Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy, gives her any other Name than <hi>Joan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, they ſay, that ſome of theſe Authors I have alledged to vindicate this truth, do claſh and differ in opinion, ſome cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling her <hi>John</hi> the 7, ſome <hi>John</hi> the 8, and others <hi>John</hi> the 9. and ſo ſaith <hi>Baronius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Baronius</hi> by his good leave quotes no Author for his Aſſertion,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:58390:57"/>and therefore I muſt beg his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don if I believe him not; for my belief ſhall extend in this no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than reaſon ſhall direct it. Beſides, whether ſhe be <hi>John</hi> the 7, or 8, the difference is not ſo great, for the like may be demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated in other Popes, whom the Romiſh party cannot deny to be Popes. But who ſtiles her <hi>John</hi> the 7, or <hi>John</hi> the 8. aſſuredly, neither <hi>Marianus Scotus, Sigibert, Gotefridus, Viterbienſis, Polonus, Platina, Palmerius, Trithemius, Faſciculus Temporum, Krantius, Alfonſus è Carthagena,</hi> nor <hi>Textor</hi> call her neither <hi>John</hi> the 7, nor <hi>John</hi> the 8, but plainly <hi>John,</hi> or <hi>Joan. Onuphrius</hi> indeed would perſwade the credulous, that <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tina</hi> ſtiles her <hi>John</hi> the 8, in theſe terms; <hi>Johannes hic omnino</hi> 8, <hi>non</hi> 9, <hi>eſt ut à Platina deſcribitur: Nam etſi Johannes foemina Papa quam pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitetur, fuiſſet, non tamen numeri na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:58390:58"/>habere debuiſſet ſacri or dinis non capax;</hi> that is, this <hi>John</hi> queſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs is the Eighth, not the Ninth, as <hi>Platina</hi> accounts him; for tho <hi>John</hi> the Woman, whom he talks of, had been Pope, yet ſeeing ſhe was not capable of Prieſt-hood, ſhe ſhould not go for one in the number of <hi>Iohns.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is another falſity; for <hi>Platina</hi> calls her not <hi>Iohn</hi> the eight, and therefore <hi>Onuphrius,</hi> or ſome perſon elſe, hath abuſed him: For proof whereof, I appeal to <hi>Platina,</hi> Printed in the year 1481, which was the year wherein <hi>Platina</hi> died, and to the next Edition 1481 who ſpeaking of <hi>Iohn</hi> the Woman in thoſe antient Editions, he pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces no numeral note on her head, but begins his Story thus, <hi>Johannes Anglicus ex Maguntiaco oriundus,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>John Engliſh</hi> born at <hi>Mentz,</hi> neither ſtiles he the next 9, but 8; for coming to that Popes life,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>i</hi> Platina mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritur Romae, Anno <hi>1481.</hi> Trithem. de Script. Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſt, verbo Bartholomaei.</note>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:58390:58"/>
               <hi>Johannes</hi> 8, <hi>Patria Romanus,</hi> &amp;c. ſaith he, <hi>Iohn</hi> the 8, by his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try a Roman, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for further proof of which later point, I appeal to the later Editions, whereunto <hi>Onu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrius</hi> his annotations are annexed; for though we read thus in them, <hi>Iohannes nonus Patria Romanus, &amp;c.</hi> yet that that reading is falſe, and the Antient reading true, appears by that which is written of the next Popes life, to wit <hi>Martin</hi> the ſecond, even in thoſe later Editi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. For<note n="l" place="margin">De vitis Pontif. in vita Martins.</note> 
               <hi>Platina</hi> ſhowing how <hi>Martin</hi> lived in the time of <hi>Charles</hi> the Third, adds preſently, <hi>Quam ab Iohanne</hi> 8, <hi>Coronam accepiſse ſcripſimus.</hi> Now <hi>Charles</hi> the third was crowned by <hi>Iohn</hi> next before <hi>Martin,</hi> according to <hi>Platina,</hi> wherefore the next before <hi>Martin</hi> was <hi>Iohn</hi> the 8, according to the opinion of the ſame man, and not <hi>Iohn</hi> the ninth, as <hi>Onuphrius</hi> would have us believe. Which overſight<note place="margin">
                  <hi>k</hi> Such as that of <hi>Colen, 1574.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:58390:59"/>or fraud of <hi>Onuphrius</hi> was not ſo great, but that by this means he is forced to alter <hi>Platina</hi> his nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral note, ſet to all the <hi>Iohns</hi> that follow to call him <hi>Iohn</hi> the tenth, whom <hi>Platina</hi> calls <hi>Iohn</hi> the ninth; to call him the eleventh, whom <hi>Platina</hi> calls the tenth, and ſo unto the laſt <hi>Baldeſar Coſſa,</hi> who was in number of <hi>Iohns</hi> according to Antient Editions the 23, and not the 24, as he is numbered in the Editions which <hi>Onuphrius</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon.</p>
            <p>Now, whereas the Romaniſts do alledge that the diſagreeing of Authors about the time wherein ſhe commenced her Papacy, and the time of her continuance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, is an argument to prove the nullity of this Story, I ſay no ſuch matter: in the firſt place, let them conſider the diſagreement that is among themſelves. Some that have written of Pope <hi>Lucius,</hi> ſay
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:58390:59"/>he was a<note n="m" place="margin">Platina in vita Lucii.</note> 
               <hi>Roman,</hi> ſome a<note n="n" place="margin">Anaſtaſius in vita Lucii.</note> 
               <hi>Tuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can,</hi> ſome ſay he was the<note n="o" place="margin">Idem. ibid.</note> Son of <hi>Lucinus,</hi> and others of<note n="p" place="margin">Plat. &amp; Onuph. loco citato.</note> 
               <hi>Porphyrie.</hi> Some ſay he was choſen Pope in the year 253, ſome 254, ſome 259, and others 275. Some ſay he ſate Pope 3 years, 3 months, and 3 days, ſome 3 years and 5 months, and ſome three years 7 months, and 6 days, which you may find in the Authors quoted in the Margent, and yet no man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies that <hi>Lucius</hi> was Pope.</p>
            <p>Again, do we not read the ſame difference in the Reign of <hi>Sergius</hi> the third; ſome will have it begin in<note n="q" place="margin">Mat. Weſt. Flores Hiſt. ad annum <hi>905.</hi>
               </note> 905, others in<note n="r" place="margin">Polon. in Chron. ad an. <hi>907.</hi>
               </note> 907, &amp;c. ſome write that he ſucceeded<note n="ſ" place="margin">Herm. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract as circa an. <hi>907.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Benedict</hi> the fourth, others that he followed<note n="t" place="margin">Luitprandi Chron.</note> 
               <hi>Formoſus,</hi> others<note n="u" place="margin">Baron. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</note> 
               <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtopher,</hi> &amp;c. yet, whoever denied that there was ſuch a Pope.</p>
            <p>We read that the Carkaſs of <hi>Formoſus</hi> was taken up out of his Grave by one of his Succeſſors,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>x</hi> Baron. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Tom. <hi>10.</hi> ad. an. <hi>897.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:58390:60"/>and brought into Judgment before a Council of Biſhops, and that it was deveſted of its Papal Robes, and clad with a Lay-mans gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that it was Indicted, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigned, and Condemned: but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe that report this, there is a great diſagreement. For ſome ſay it was taken up by <hi>Sergius</hi> the third, ſome by <hi>Steven</hi> the ſixth, ſome ſay it had two fingers cut off, ſome three; ſome ſay the Head was chopt off, and ſome deny it; ſome ſay the Trunk was thrown into <hi>Tyber,</hi> and ſome ſay it had Lay-mans Burial: and yet who of the Romaniſts will deny the truth of this Story, by reaſon of theſe differences. <hi>Onuphrius</hi> denies it point blank, ſaying, <hi>quae de For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſi cadavere ex Sepultura à ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoribus eruto dicuntur, proculdubio fabulae magis quam vero ſimilia ſunt, quod illorum qui de ea re ſcripſerunt diverſitate &amp; repugnantia facile li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet.</hi>
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:58390:60"/>The report which goes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the digging up <hi>Formoſus</hi> body out of his Grave by ſome of his Succeſſors, are queſtionleſs ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulous and not true, which is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent by the diſagreement, and diſconveniencies which are to be found among them who write of it. Notwithſtanding the manifold differences in circumſtances, <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronius</hi> durſt not caſt it off, as <hi>Onu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrius.</hi> For he ingeniouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth, it was ſuch a villainous prank, as was never plaid before; <hi>Intentatum hactenus ſcelus,</hi> and by reaſon of its barbarouſneſs incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible; <hi>prae ſui immanitate omnibus incredibile;</hi> yet he grants it true, and avows that they foully err, who deny what was done to the carkaſs of <hi>Formoſus,</hi> looking on the report no better than a Fable.<note n="h" place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> de Rom. Pont. cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bellarmin</hi> ſaith true in this, that <hi>ſaepiſſime accidit, ut conſtet de re &amp; non conſtet de modo vel alia circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantia.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>g</hi> Annal Tom. <hi>10.</hi> ad an. <hi>897.</hi> nu. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:58390:61"/>It often happens, that men are ſure ſuch a thing is done, when yet they are not ſure of the manner how it was done, or of ſome other ſuch like circumſtance. The dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference among Witers about cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance doth not weaken any mans argument touching the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: if it do, I would have the Romaniſts for ſhame blot out St. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſula</hi> and her fellows Holy-day out of their<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Octob.</hi> 21.</note> Kalendar, and all the Prayers they make to them in their Primers, Porteſſes, and Breviaries; for there was never greater diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreement among the Relators of any Story, than among the Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of that. Some ſay, that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſula</hi> was the King of <hi>Scotlands</hi> Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, others ſay the King of <hi>Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>walls</hi> Daughter; ſome ſay her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was called <hi>Maurus,</hi> others <hi>Dionethus,</hi> or <hi>Dionatus,</hi> or <hi>Dioni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus:</hi> the Husband ſhe was to marry, ſome ſay, was King of
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:58390:61"/>
               <hi>Little-Brittain,</hi> and one calls him <hi>Aetherius,</hi> another <hi>Holofernes,</hi> and a third <hi>Conanus.</hi> Now in her company they ſay there were only 11000 Ladies and Gentlewomen, all Virgins, others ſay there were 60000 Country Maidens over and above: beſides, there were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Biſhops, and Lords temporal, who accompanied them; yea, <hi>Cyriacus</hi> the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> like a good fellow, and a <hi>Truſty Trojan,</hi> left his Papacy, and followed theſe Pilgrims, as ſome ſay, though o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers deny it. For ſome ſay they went in pilgrimage to <hi>Rome,</hi> though others do not hold that probable: ſome ſay they were martyred on the Sea-coaſt; ſome ſay before the Gates of <hi>Colen.</hi> Laſtly, ſome ſay that if any be buried in St. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſula</hi>'s Church, though they be Infants newly baptized, the ground will caſt them up again; though others ſay
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:58390:62"/>that that is a tale of a Tub, and others ſay it is as damn'd a lye as e're was hatcht.</p>
            <p>But to proceed, our Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries do ſay, that <hi>Athens</hi> was ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly deſtroyed at that time, when it was ſtoried <hi>John Engliſh,</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Pope <hi>Joan</hi> travel'd thither, as a Trickery Mate with her lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Companion, to ſtudy Arts and Sciences. I utterly deny it, for <hi>Paulus</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 8.</note> 
               <hi>Aemilius</hi> writes, that <hi>Gotefridus</hi> was made Duke of <hi>Athens,</hi> and Prince of <hi>Achaia</hi> about the year 1220, and afterwards that certain Pirates invading the Country of <hi>Greece,</hi> ſlew the Duke of <hi>Athens,</hi> who was of the houſe of <hi>Brennas,</hi> and took the City. In like manner we read in<note n="l" place="margin">In Hen. <hi>3.</hi> ad an. <hi>1252.</hi> pag. <hi>1112.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Mat. Paris,</hi> that <hi>Johannes de Baſing-ſtocks, Arch-Deacon of Legria,</hi> who died in the year 1252. ſtudied at <hi>Athens,</hi> and that there he learned many things unknown to the We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:58390:62"/>Churches. Beſides <hi>Aeneas Sylvus,</hi> who lived ſince that, doth juſtify that in his time <hi>Athens</hi> was not totally demoliſhed, but car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the ſhew of a pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tty Town. For <hi>Civitas Athenienſis</hi> (quoth he) <hi>quondam nobiliſſima fuit, &amp;c. eadem noſtro tempore parvi oppidi ſpeciem g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rit.</hi> So that the exception afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, doth no way prejudice the truth of this Story.</p>
            <p>Having driven them from this poor Sconce, this ſlender ſhelter, I ſhall purſue them to another, which is grounded on what <hi>C. Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmin</hi> writes, <hi>That there were no Schools for learning at that time, neither in</hi> Athens, <hi>nor any part of</hi> Graecia, (ſaith he)<note n="m" place="margin">Lib. <hi>3.</hi> de Rom. Pontif. cap. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Conſtat eo tempore neque Athenis neque uſquam alibi in Graecia fuiſſe ulla Gymnaſia literarum.</hi> This he endeavours to prove, firſt by <hi>Syneſius,</hi> who lived a little after St. <hi>Baſil,</hi> and <hi>Nazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anzens</hi> time, who<note n="n" place="margin">In Epiſt. ult. ad fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem ſuum.</note> writ to his
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:58390:63"/>Brother, that <hi>Athens</hi> retained only the bare name of an Univerſity. And ſecondly, he makes uſe of <hi>Zonoras</hi> and <hi>Cedrenus</hi> to back the former, who record, that in the ſole Reign of <hi>Michael</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, about the year 856, <hi>Bernar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus Caeſar</hi> reſtored Learning, <hi>Cum uſque ad illud tempus per annos plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimos ita fuiſſent extincta omnia ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia ſapientia in Graecia, ut ne veſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gium quidem ullum extaret.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And doth this import think you, that in <hi>Syneſiius</hi> his opinion there was no <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity</hi> at <hi>Athens:</hi> I am of the opinion that <hi>Syneſius</hi> meant thereby, that <hi>Athens</hi> was an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity,</hi> though nothing near ſo famous and flouriſhing as heretofore, Queſtionelſs when<note n="o" place="margin">Bernardi Epiſt. <hi>193.</hi>
               </note> St. <hi>Bernard</hi> writ, that <hi>Peter Abailard</hi> had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of a Monk, but the name, and the Cowl, his meaning was not that <hi>Peter</hi> was no Monk, but a ſory one. And I am the rather
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:58390:63"/>induced to underſtand the words of <hi>Syneſius</hi> to be ſo: becauſe <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> in St, <hi>Baſils</hi> time (about ſome 40 years before <hi>Syneſius</hi>) was held the <hi>Mother of Learning,</hi> and in regard therof called <hi>Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Athens</hi> by <hi>Greg.</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">In Monodia in Baſ Magni vitam.</note> 
               <hi>Nazianzen.</hi> For who can think in ſo few years, Learning ſhould quite be quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and that ſo famous an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity</hi> ſhould in ſo ſhort a time be utterly decayed; but ſuppoſe there was no <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity</hi> in <hi>Athens</hi> in <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſius</hi> his time: what is that to prove there was no <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity</hi> in <hi>Pope Joans</hi> time at <hi>Athens,</hi> which was 400 years after? That <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity</hi> might revive, and get new Life in ſo many years; as it did: for two years after <hi>Syneſius</hi> his time, <hi>Boethius</hi> went to ſtudy at <hi>Athens, teſte Baronio,</hi> adding further that the ſtudy of Philoſophy was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived there in thoſe days.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>p</hi> Baron. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. Tom. <hi>3.</hi> ad an. <hi>354.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <pb n="120" facs="tcp:58390:64"/>
            <p>As for <hi>Cedrenus,</hi> and <hi>Zonorus, Bellarmin</hi> wrongs them both in bringing them in to witneſs, that there were no Schools in any part of <hi>Graecia</hi> in <hi>Pope Joans</hi> times. For they ſay no more, but that Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was not regarded a long time before <hi>Bardus Caeſar:</hi> they do not ſay that it was quite extinct, but almoſt: <hi>Philoſophia neglecta jacebat, ac propè omnino extincta erat, ut ne ſcintilla quidem ejus apparet.</hi> Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus Caeſar <hi>added Life to it by erect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Schools for all the Liberal Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and appointing Publick Profeſſors, and giving them ſtipends out of the Exchequer,</hi> as <hi>Cedrenus</hi> and <hi>Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noras</hi> do writ; but certainly he raiſed it not up ſimply to Life; for had it been ſtark dead, how could he ſo ſuddainly have gotten Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors to furniſh his Schools? We may read in <hi>Zonoras,</hi> that at the ſame time there was a matchleſs Philoſopher called <hi>Leo</hi> who ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:58390:64"/>at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and had to his Scholars many skilful Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticians. Moreover it cannot be denyed, that about the year 680 there was kept a General Council at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> wherein there were many eminent Biſhops of <hi>Greece,</hi> and among the reſt the<note n="r" place="margin">Conc. Conſt. <hi>6.</hi> Act. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> Biſhop of <hi>Athens.</hi> There was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Council kept at <hi>Nice,</hi> and 100 years after, <hi>viz.</hi> about the 780 at which there were more Biſhops of <hi>Greece,</hi> than at the former. There was a third Council held at <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> which did exceed in number either of the former two, about the year<note n="t" place="margin">Bellarm. loco citat.</note> 870: and how is it credible ſo many Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils conſiſting of many Biſhops ſhould be kept in <hi>Greece,</hi> and yet <hi>Greece</hi> utterly without Learning.</p>
            <p>Now as theſe abuſers of truth deny that there was any Learning at that time in <hi>Greece,</hi> ſo they will not allow that there was any<note place="margin">
                  <hi>ſ</hi> Bellar. lib. <hi>1.</hi> de Conc. cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:58390:65"/>open Profeſſion of Learning in thoſe days in <hi>Rome,</hi> becauſe they will gainſay the truth of <hi>Pope Joans</hi> going thither, and that as ſhe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed publickly all manner of Learning, whereby the greateſt Doctors there became her Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, ſo ſhe preached, and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully ingaged the Ears, and Hearts of her Auditors.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Mat. Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. Flores Hiſt. ad an. <hi>727.</hi>
               </note>Hiſtory makes appear, that <hi>Ina</hi> (one of our Saxon Kings) did build a School in <hi>Rome</hi> a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the days of <hi>Pope Joan</hi> in the year 727, to this end, that the Kings of England, and their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, the Biſhops, Prieſts, and the reſt of the Clergy might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair thither to be inſtructed in the Catholick faith, and afterwards return home, which School flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed in the raign of King<note n="x" place="margin">Ibid. ad an. <hi>794.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Offa</hi> which was in the year 795, and continued at leaſt till <hi>Alfred</hi>'s time. For we Read, that <hi>Marinus,</hi> who
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:58390:65"/>was Pope in the year 883, freed it from all payments at the requeſt of <hi>Alfred.</hi> Now is it likely that ſuch a School was built, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd for ſuch a purpoſe, where no Learning was publickly profeſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? Moreover we read of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Schools kept in the ſame City, in the time of <hi>Steven</hi> the 6, in the year 885. For all the Schools in <hi>Rome</hi> with alacrity concurred, and brought <hi>Steven</hi> the ſixth to the <hi>Palace of Lateran,</hi> and <hi>Stephen</hi> was troubled, he had not wherewith to gratify them: thus ſaith <hi>Anaſtaſius</hi> in the Life of this Pope; and is it reaſon to believe theſe Schools were without Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, Readers, and Profeſſors?</p>
            <p>But now it is time to introduce that which <hi>Cardinal Baronius</hi> thinks will knock 'ith' head and bury this ſtory in perpetual oblivion; and that is thus; ſaith he, <hi>if Leo the fourth lived to the year</hi> 855, <hi>then Marianus Scotus, the firſt promoter
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:58390:66"/>of this ſtory, told a manifeſt untruth, in reporting that this Joan was choſen Pope in the year</hi> 853; <hi>for by his confeſſion ſhe ſucceeded Leo the</hi> 4, <hi>but Leo the</hi> 4 <hi>lived to the year</hi> 855; <hi>Ergo Marianus Scotus lyes,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Anno octingenteſſimo quinquageſimo tertio, Leo Papa, obiit Kalend. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſti; huic ſucceſſ it Johanna Mulier annis duobus, menſibus quinque, die<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus quatuor. In the year</hi> 853 <hi>Leo the Pope died on the Kalends of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt, and Joan the woman ſucceeded af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him for the ſpace of two years, five months, and four days.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You may ſee the falacy of this Cardinal; for theſe are not <hi>Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus</hi> words, for he ſets not down the year preciſely, but in numeral figures in the Margent. And it is plain by conference of years, that he meant to note out the 855 for her entrance, and not the 853. For <hi>Benedict</hi> the 3. who ſucceeded her, entred not by his account till the year 857; now if ſhe had entied<note place="margin">
                  <hi>y</hi> Conſult Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rianus Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle and you will be throughly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfyed.</note>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:58390:66"/>in 853, ſhe had been Pope 4 years, or there abouts: whereas he plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly notes, that ſhe was Pope but two years, five months, and four days. Secondly, it is plain by <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rianus Scotus,</hi> that <hi>Sergius</hi> the 2 began his Popedom in the year 844 and ſate 3 years; and it is as plain, that <hi>Leo</hi> the 4, next ſucceſſor to <hi>Sergius,</hi> began his in the year 847, and ſate 8 years; now add theſe three odd ſums to 840, and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct will be 855, ſo that whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſucceeded <hi>Leo</hi> the 4, muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin in the year 855, and that was <hi>Joan the Woman Pope</hi> in <hi>Marianus</hi> his opinion.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Flor. in c. <hi>25.</hi> nu. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Florimondus</hi> would make us believe, that the Moon is made of a Green Cheeſe; for, (ſays he) we read nothing in Hiſtory of her reforming the Church; of her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termining of cauſes, and queſtions uſually propoſed by Biſhops to them that are Popes; of any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercourſe,
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:58390:67"/>or affairs that ſhe had with King, or Emperour; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore certainly, had there been any ſuch <hi>Joan</hi> a <hi>Pope,</hi> her actions, as well as her bare name would have been regiſtred by Hiſtorians.</p>
            <p>He might as well queſtion, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there ever was an <hi>Anaſtaſius</hi> the third, who ſate two years, and upward, and yet no Hiſtorian tells what he did in that affair; only <hi>Platina</hi> writes, he acted nothing worth commemoration. We read of no great matter done by <hi>Leo</hi> the ſeventh, who ſate 3 years 6 months, and was as very a Drone as the other, for any thing we read; he neither reformed the Church, nor reſolved any Biſhop his doubts, nor intermedled with the affairs of Princes; and whereas the Author aforeſaid may pretend, that in that age wherein <hi>Pope Joan</hi> li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, there was great controverſies between the <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſtern</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>a</hi> Platina in vita Anaſtaſii <hi>3</hi> nil memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria dignum Ceſtum eſt.</note>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:58390:67"/>
               <hi>Church,</hi> that in it many Princes and Emperours reigned, who were as much ſignalized for their virtue, as royal dignity: that in it many men of great learning lived, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if there had been any ſuch monſter then, they could not have paſt her by in ſilence. No more they did, as I have already pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, neither was there more va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of matter fell out in that age, than ordinary; though ſome would have us believe, that between the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> and <hi>Weſtern Churches,</hi> there was a great controverſy, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention about <hi>Images,</hi> and that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Councils</hi> were held, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> this is a poſitive untruth; for all ſtories teſtify, that the difference between thoſe two <hi>Churches</hi> about <hi>Images,</hi> began in the former ages; and that though they continued ſome few years after the year 800. yet there was no talk of that matter for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe years before <hi>Pope Joans</hi> days.
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:58390:68"/>And as for the Learned men of that age, <hi>Baronius</hi> gives an account of them; <hi>qui ſciret tantum Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticam iſto ſeculo rudi, Doc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſsimus habebatur.</hi> Theſe went for learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men in that age, who were but bare Grammarians: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were they never ſo many, <hi>Pope Joans</hi> acts might paſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written.</p>
            <p>If any conjecture that this <hi>Pope Joan</hi> did never inaugure, and crown Dukes, Princes, Kings, or Emperors, I may anſwer, did e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Pope inaugure, and crown them, and though our Antagoniſts ſay, that in that age the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours themſelves had ſuch a reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend eſteem of the <hi>Roman</hi> Popes, that they would not undertake the rule, and government of their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, except they gave them their conſent, and crowned them; and for proof of this they alledg, that <hi>Adrian</hi> the firſt baptized two Sons<note place="margin">
                  <hi>b</hi> Baron. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. Tom. <hi>9.</hi> ad an. <hi>802.</hi> nu. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note>
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:58390:68"/>of <hi>Charles</hi> the great, and after that anointed them Kings.</p>
            <p>This is eaſily anſwer'd, for this happened in the year 781, as<note n="c" place="margin">Baron. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. Tom. <hi>9.</hi> ad an. nu. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronius</hi> obſerves and not in that age wherein <hi>Pope Joan</hi> lived. It is not to be imagin'd that every Pope in that age inaugured ſome Dukes, Princes, Kings, or Emperours; for we do not find that <hi>Eugenius</hi> the Second in the year 824; <hi>Valenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> in 827; <hi>Gregory</hi> the 4 who ſucceeded him; <hi>Sergius</hi> the 2 in 844, or <hi>Pope Leo the</hi> 4, who ſate in the year 847 inaugured, or crowned any of them, but this Pope laſt mention'd, who anointed <hi>Alfred,</hi> the youngeſt Son of <hi>Athel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wulſus</hi> King of <hi>England</hi> which aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted him not, nor further'd him to the attaining of the Kingdom; for till the Death of his three Elder Brethren, notwithſtanding the Popes anointing, he lived like a Subject, not like a King, wherefore
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:58390:69"/>though <hi>Pope Joan</hi> inaugur'd, or crowned no ſuch Perſons, it muſt not thereupon be concluded, there was no <hi>Pope Ioan.</hi> But this we read, that <hi>contulit ſacros ordines, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>movit Epiſcopos, miniſtravit Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta, caeteraque Romanorum Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificum exercuit munera;</hi> ſhe gave Orders, ſhe made Biſhops, ſhe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred the Sacraments, and performed all other offices belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Papacy; this truth is teſtifyed not only by <hi>Iohn Bal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> but by<note n="d" place="margin">De vanitate Scient cap. <hi>62.</hi> de ſectis Monaſticis.</note> 
               <hi>Cornelius Agrippa,</hi> a man highly commended by<note n="e" place="margin">Lib. <hi>1</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtol, Epiſt. <hi>38.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Leo</hi> the 10, and in a Book of his ſolemnly pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledged by <hi>Charles</hi> the 5.</p>
            <p>And let me not forget to anſwer one grand objection more, which the Papiſts alledge againſt the truth of this ſtory; <hi>Ratio i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tabilis,</hi> ſaith <hi>Genebrard</hi> in his Chronology, and this is it.<note n="f" place="margin">Leo <hi>9</hi> Epiſt. ad Michael. Epiſc. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinop. cap. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note> About 170 years after this invented fabulous election of <hi>Pope Ioan,</hi> in the year of our Lord
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:58390:69"/>1020, the Church, and the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch, of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> being in ſome contention with Rome, <hi>Leo</hi> the 9 wrote a Letter to <hi>Michael</hi> the Patriarch of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending certain abuſes of that Church, and among others that they were ſaid to have promoted Eunuchs to Prieſthood, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by alſo a greater inconvenience fallen out, that a woman had craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily crept in to be a Patriarch. Now no doubt (ſay they) <hi>Leo</hi> would never have durſt to write thus, if the Patriarch might have returned the matter back upon him again, and ſaid, this was but a ſlanderous report, falſly raiſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Church of <hi>Conſtantinople<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> but that a woman indeed had been promoted in the Roman Church.</p>
            <p>This argument is very weak in my judgment, for any to preſume in this, that <hi>Leo would never object that againſt Conſtantinople,</hi> whereof
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:58390:70"/>
               <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf might be convinced; to prove this no unanſwearable ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, it is uſual for the Papiſts to object that againſt others, whereof they themſelves ſtand moſt guilty; and with the Proverb, <hi>cry Whore firſt.</hi> How do they exclaim againſt the Clergy of <hi>England</hi> for want of Continency? and yet is it not well known, how their Prieſts, and Monks, like<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jerem.</hi> 5.8.</note> fed horſes, have nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghed after their Neighbours Wives, and their Nuns have opened their feet (to uſe the<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezech.</hi> 16.25.</note> Prophets phraſe when he ſpeaketh of ſuch like Light-skirts) to every one that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by, and have multiplied their Whoredoms. <hi>Taceo de fornicatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus, et adulteriis a quibus qui alieni ſunt, probro caeteris ac ludibrio eſſe ſolent Spadoneſque, aut Sodomitae ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellantur,</hi> ſaith<note n="i" place="margin">De Praſuli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Simoniacis in Bibliothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca Patrum. Paris <hi>1576.</hi> p. <hi>655.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nich. Clemangis,</hi> ſpeaking of the Romiſh Prieſts. I ſay nothing of your Prieſts fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and adulteries, from which
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:58390:70"/>crimes, if any man be free, he is made a laughing ſtock to the reſt, and either called an <hi>Eunuch</hi> or a <hi>Sodomite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laici uſque adeo perſuaſum ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent nullos caelibes eſſe, ut in pleriſque parochiis non alitervelint Preſbyterum tolerare, niſi Concubinam habeat: quovel ſic ſuis ſit conſultum uxoribus, quae ne ſic quidem uſquequaque ſunt extra periculum,</hi> ſaith the ſame man. The Lay people are ſo convinced of the incontinence of all Prieſts, that, willingly they would not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of a Pariſh Prieſt, unleſs he have a Whore of his own, that ſo they might preſerve the Chaſtity of their own Wives; and yet fall ſhort of their expectations, by reaſon of the leachery of the Prieſts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fornicantur complures Monialium cum ſuis Praelatis, ac Monachis, et converſis, et in Monaſteriis plures parturiunt filios, et filias quos ab iiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Praelatis Monachis et Converſis
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:58390:71"/>fornicarie, ſeu ex inceſtuoſo coitu con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceperunt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Theodoricus de Niem,</hi> Secretary to Pope <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the 6, thus proceeding, <hi>et quod miſerandum eſt nonnullae ex hujuſmodi Moniali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus aliquos foetus earum mortificant, infantes in lucem editos trucidant,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Nuns</hi> commited fornication with Biſhops, <hi>Monks,</hi> and <hi>Converts,</hi> and are delivered of ſons and daughters within their <hi>Monaſteries,</hi> which were got by thoſe Perſons Fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor-like, if not inceſtuouſly; and which is moſt to be lamented, very many of theſe <hi>Nuns</hi> by internal re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions deſtroy the fruit of their womb; and many kill them after they are born.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Clemangis de corrupto Eccleſ. ſtatu.</note>
               <hi>Quid obſecro aliud ſunt hoc tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llarum Monaſteria, niſi quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam Veneris execranda proſtibula &amp; Iaſoivorum, et impudicorum juvenum ad libidines explendas receptacula? ut idem ſit bodie puellam velare, quod &amp; publice ad ſcortandum exponere?</hi>
               <pb n="135" facs="tcp:58390:71"/>what are <hi>Nunneries</hi> I pray now, but curſed <hi>Stews,</hi> and <hi>Meeting-places</hi> for wanton, and ſhameleſs youth to ſatisfy their luſts in? So that now it is all one to make a <hi>Wench</hi> a <hi>Nun,</hi> and to make her a <hi>Whore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note n="l" place="margin">He. Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingdon, hiſt. lib. <hi>7.</hi> ad ann. <hi>1125.</hi> Roger Hoveden An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. pars prior in Hen. <hi>1.1126.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Johannes Cremenſis,</hi> a Romiſh Cardinal, held a Council at <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> in the year 1125, wherein he inveighed bitterly againſt ſuch Prieſts, as kept Concubines, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>ſummum ſcelus eſſe a latere me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retricis ad corpus Chriſti conficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ſurgere;</hi> it was a damnable ſin for a Prieſt to ariſe from the ſide of a Whore, and go and adminiſter the Body of Chriſt; yet he himſelf loved a Whore with all his heart; for we may read in our Engliſh Stories, <hi>ipſe cum eodem die Corpus Chriſti confeciſſet cum meretrice poſt veſperam interceptus eſt;</hi> he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was taken with a Whore the ſame night after he had ſaid <hi>Maſs, ipſo facto.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="136" facs="tcp:58390:72"/>
            <p>Again, they condemn us of ignorance, ſaying, we dare not diſpute with them in matter of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and if any of us are ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, we are eaſily baffled, being not able to produce ſo many argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in our own defence as our<note n="m" place="margin">Briſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>riu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> Adverſaries do for us, applaud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves, and debaſing us, and yet it is eaſy to prove that their Prieſts, and Monks are generally like the threeſcore thouſand<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jonas.</hi> 4.11.</note> 
               <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivites,</hi> who had not ſo much wit as to diſcern between their left hand, and their right.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Videas admitti in Sacerdotium caeteroſque ſacros ordines homines i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diotas &amp; illiteratos,</hi> &amp;c. ſaith <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mangis,</hi> ſpeaking of the ignorance of the Romiſh Clergy, thou maiſt ſee ignorant and illiterate perſons advanced to the Prieſt-hood and other holy orders, which can hardly read; and farther complains; how many are there now adays preferr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:58390:72"/>to Biſhopricks, who ſo much as curſorily have neither read, or heard, or learned the holy Scriptures: and ſaith<note n="o" place="margin">De Sac. eccleſ. Miniſt. Beneſ. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Duarenus, Hoc ſaeculo Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copatus &amp; Sacerdotia indoctiſsimis hominibus, &amp; a religione alienis de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferri ſolent— hodie Epiſcopi noſtri (paucis exceptis) ſacrarum literarum ſcientia caeteris ex populo longe infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riores ſunt.</hi> In this age Biſhopricks and Perſonages are beſtowed on moſt unlearned and irreligious men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſaith,<note n="p" place="margin">Comment. de dictis &amp; fact. Alfonſ. Regis lib. <hi>2.</hi> Apothegm. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Aeneas Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius, pudeat Italiae ſacerdotes, quos ne ſemel quidem legiſſe conſtat novam L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gem.</hi> It is a ſhame to <hi>Italy</hi> that her Prieſts never read over the New Teſtament: and as another ſays, <hi>Eccleſiarum regimina minus dignis (Romae videlice<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>) committuntur qui ad Malos magis quam homines pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendos &amp; regendos eſſent idonei,</hi> that the government of the Churches even at <hi>Rome,</hi> is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited to unworthy Perſons, who
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:58390:73"/>are fitter to look to the keeping of Mules than Men.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="q" place="margin">De corrupto Eccleſ. ſtatu.</note>
               <hi>Clemangis</hi> ſpeaking of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Worthies, ſaith, <hi>Siquis deſidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſus eſt, ſiquis a labore abhorrens ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis in otio luxuriari volens ad ſacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotium convolat: quo adepto, ſe ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim caeteris ſacerdotibus adjungit, qui magis ſecundum Epicurum, quam ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum Chriſtum viventes &amp; cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponulas ſeduli frequentantes, potan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do commeſſando, pranſitando convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vando cum teſſaris &amp; pilo ludendo tempora tota conſumunt,</hi> &amp;c. If there be any lazie fellow, one that will not work, but indulge his ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes he is reſtleſs till he is be-prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and when he is made one, and hath gotten a Benefice, he conſorts with his fellow Prieſts as ſenſual as himſelf, and then he and they live more like Epicures than Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; Drinking, Eating, Revel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Playing, Damming and being tippled, Swear and Fight, whilſt
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:58390:73"/>others as they come reaking hot from filthy carnal ſatisfactions, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs themſelves to the Holy Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aſciſcuntur nunc</hi> (ſaith<note n="r" place="margin">In vita So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zimi.</note> 
               <hi>Platina</hi>) <hi>non modo ſervi &amp; vulgo concepti ac nati verum etiam flagitioſo quoque geniti.</hi> Now adays not only Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants and vulgar Perſons are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited to be of the Clergy, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very vile fellow, and the brats of ſuch like Perſons.</p>
            <p>And ſaith<note n="ſ" place="margin">Panopliae lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>77.</hi> p. <hi>405.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Lindan, ex Aulicis per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditiſſimus &amp; quod omni aetate fuit poſt Chriſti annorum memoriam in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>auditam ex militibus deploratiſſimis iiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſanguinariis Dei loco ad Eccleſiae collocantur; imo repente intruduntur gubernacula quid quod puerilis &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doleſcentulis creduntur haec tractanda.</hi> The worſt of Courtiers forlorn and bloody Soldiers (a thing never heard of before among Chriſtians) are all on a ſuddain thruſt in upon the Church to manage it in Gods
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:58390:74"/>ſtead, yea, Boys and youngſters are made Biſhops and Prelates in the Church.</p>
            <p>As the Papiſts tax us with igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>race, ſo they do with falſehood, of which they themſelves are moſt guilty. For inſtance<note n="t" place="margin">In Epiſtola <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. ad Impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rem.</note> 
               <hi>Agatho</hi> a Pope avoucheth, that the Roman Church never ſwarved from the tradition of the Apoſtles, that ſhe never gave Ear to novelties, that the Popes Predeceſſors had ever boldly ſtrengthened their Brethren accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Chriſts commandment to <hi>Peter;</hi> for proof hereof, he appeals to all the world. In like manner <hi>Pope Nicolas</hi> boaſts, that none of the Popes was ever ſuſpected to have held an errour; and <hi>Victor</hi> was ſuppoſed to have held, that Chriſt was pure man and not God, which is atteſted by<note n="x" place="margin">Hiſt. Eccl. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>28.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Euſebius: Zepherinus</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>u</hi> In Epiſtola <hi>1.</hi> ad Michae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</note> was ſuſpected of <hi>Montaniſm,</hi> ſo ſaith<note n="y" place="margin">Contra Praxe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m.</note> 
               <hi>Tertullian: Marcellinus</hi> ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed to Idols according to<note n="z" place="margin">In Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cali in vita Marcelli.</note> 
               <hi>Dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi>
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:58390:74"/>his report, and acknowledged by <hi>Bellarmin,</hi> though denyed in part by <hi>Baronius: Liberius</hi> ſubſcribed to the <hi>Arian</hi> hereſy, ſo ſay <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>hanaſius, Jerome</hi> and <hi>Sozomen,</hi> and to be ſhort, that <hi>Honorius</hi> the firſt was a Monothelite, and for that condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by name in the ſixth and ſeventh general Councils. From hence I ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that <hi>Pope Agatho</hi> was not In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible in his judgment, neither am I apt to believe that the Sons of that Church are leſs fallible. It is not their bare ſaying that this is ſo and that not ſo, but the proof they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce muſt be conſider'd, according to validity.</p>
            <p>And now the Papiſts, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hardly what to ſay for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſuggeſt this,<note n="a" place="margin">Onuph. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at. in Plat. in vita Johan. <hi>8.</hi> Harding in his Anſwer <hi>10</hi> Ep. Jewel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Apology.</note> that though men at that time had been ſo far be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched or mope-eyed, as not to diſtinguiſh a man from a woman, yet God himſelf, who appointed and ordained the Seat of <hi>Peter</hi> to be
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:58390:75"/>the rule and direction of the whole Church, ſhould never have depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo far from his merciful provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, as to ſuffer the ſame to be poluted by a woman incapacita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for holy orders, and a <hi>Puttana Errant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> to boot.</p>
            <p>I would willingly underſtand why might not the Almighty ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer that Church to be polluted by a Woman, as by ſo many Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Beaſts of Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, as ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Pontificial Writers have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, who ingeniouſly, rather than they would prejudice, have confeſſed the wild actions of their brethren to their everlaſting ſhame and infamy. Why might ſhe not fit there as well as<note n="b" place="margin">Faſcicul. Temp. ad an. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sabinian,</hi> whom though a Pope, I muſt call by reaſon of his exorbitant wicked life; I cannot call that miſcreant by a name bad enough, and as he lived ſinfully, he died fearfully. VVhy might ſhe not ſit there as
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:58390:75"/>well as <hi>Stephen</hi> the 6, who dig'd up the Carkaſs of Pope <hi>Formoſus</hi> his Predeceſſor, and as if living, had it arraign'd before a Council of Biſhops, and condemn'd, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as I have afore recited. VVhy might She not ſit there as well as<note n="c" place="margin">Plat. in vita Bonif.</note> 
               <hi>Boniface</hi> the ſeventh, who rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed St. <hi>Peters</hi> Church, and fled for a time to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> who after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards by Simony, and the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of two Popes, got into the Papacy, who in miſchief, excelled all the Ruſſins and Bandities of his time for cruelty, and for the Ruin of his Country <hi>Sylla</hi> and <hi>Cataline</hi> come ſhort of him. Thus much<note n="d" place="margin">Annal. Tom. <hi>10.</hi> ad annum <hi>985.</hi> nu. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Baronius</hi> confeſſeth, and at length as he lived like a Brute, ſo he dyed like a Beaſt; theſe are his words, <hi>Bonifacius</hi> 7 <hi>annumerandus inter Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſos latrones &amp; potentiſſimos graſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores atque patriae proditores Syllas &amp; Catalinas horumque ſimiles quosomnes ſuperavit ſacrilegus iſte turpiſſima
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:58390:76"/>nece duorum Pontiſicum.</hi> And why might ſhe not ſit there as well as <hi>Sylveſter</hi> the 2 that famous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurer, who gave himſelf both body and Soul to the Devil, that he might get the Popedom, and whilſt living was hurryed away whither no mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ever yet could tell. <hi>Platina,</hi> in his Lives of the Popes, writes thus of him, that <hi>ambitione &amp; diabolica dominandi cupiditate impulſus, largi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione primo quidem Archiep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcopatum Rhemenſem inde Ravennatem a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deptus Pontificatum, poſtremo majore conatu adjuvante Diabolo conſequu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus eſt hac tamen lege ut poſt mortem totus illius eſſet cujus fraudibus tantam dignitate adep us erat: Sylveſter</hi> the 2, being damnable ambitious, got firſt by bribery the Arch Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick of <hi>Rhemes,</hi> then that of <hi>Raven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> and after that by the Devils help, the Biſhoprick of <hi>Rome,</hi> yet upon this condition, that when he dyed he ſhould be wholly his, by
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:58390:76"/>whoſe means he had attained ſuch dignity: <hi>Sigibert</hi> confeſſeth in a manner the ſame thing, for he ſaith, <hi>non per oſtium intrare creditur,</hi> he got the Popedom by indirect courſe, for <hi>a quibuſdam Negroman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae arguitur,</hi> he was ſuſpected of <hi>Negromancy;</hi> the like is affirmed by Cardinal<note n="e" place="margin">De vita &amp; geſtis Hilde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brandi.</note> 
               <hi>Benno,</hi> by<note n="f" place="margin">In Chron. ad an. <hi>1007</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus Polonus,</hi> by<note n="g" place="margin">De vitis Pontif. in Sylveſt. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Stella</hi> a <hi>Venetian,</hi> by<note n="h" place="margin">Supplement. Chron. ad an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num <hi>997</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Philippus Bergomenſis,</hi> by<note n="i" place="margin">In Polychron. lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>14.</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Ranulfus Ceſtrenſis,</hi> by <hi>Matthaeus Weſtmonaſterienſis,</hi> by <hi>Faſciculus Temporum,</hi> by <hi>Charanza,</hi> and by <hi>Aeneas Sylvius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Malmsbury,</hi> having related the ſame Story in effect with the above named Writers, ſuppoſeth that ſome might reply, this is but a made Tale, <hi>Sed haec vulgata ficta crederet, aliquis eo quod ſolet Populus literatorum famam lae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere dicens illum, loqui cum Daemone quem in aliquo viderint excellentem opere;</hi> becauſe the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:58390:77"/>are wont to ſay, that Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, who are ſingular or excellent in any thing, are cunning men, or deal with the Devil; yet he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes, that he believes it for true, for <hi>mihi vero fidem facit de iſtius ſacrilegio inaudita mortis excogitatio,</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> de geſtis Rerum Aug. cap. <hi>10.</hi> fol. <hi>36.</hi>
               </note> ſaith he, I am verily perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Sylveſter</hi> was ſuch a Villain, becauſe of the ſtrangeneſs of his death, <hi>Nam curſe moriens excar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificaret ipſe ſui corpor is horrendus Laniſta niſi novi ſceleris conſcius eſſet?</hi> For why ſhould the But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherly fellow have torn his own fleſh as he did, but that he was guilty of ſome ſtrange ſin.</p>
            <p>To proceed, why might not Pope <hi>Joan</hi> ſit in the Papal Chair as well as <hi>Benedict</hi> the ninth tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ugly Monſter, as <hi>Platina</hi> calls him, <hi>Teterrimum Monſtrum,</hi> who got the Popedom when he was 12 years old,<note n="l" place="margin">Sigonius de Regno Italiae, lib. <hi>7.</hi> ad an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num <hi>1048.</hi>
               </note> who when he was caſt out for his unworthineſs by ſtrong hand,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:58390:77"/>got it again within few dayes after, and for fear he could not keep it long, ſold it to another for mony: who after his Death appeared partly like an Aſs, partly like a Bear, confeſſing that he carried ſuch a ſhape, becauſe he lived ſo much like a Beaſt in his life.</p>
            <p>Why might ſhe not ſit in St. <hi>Peters</hi> Chair as well as<note n="m" place="margin">Pet. Crini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus de honeſta diſcip. lib. <hi>8.</hi> cap. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Boniface</hi> the eight, who when according to cuſtome, on <hi>Aſh-Wedneſday,</hi> when he ſhould have laid aſhes upon an Arch-biſhops head, and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly told him, that he was but Aſhes, and ſhould return to Aſhes, he caſt them in the Arch-Biſhops face and eyes, malitiouſly telling him, that he was a <hi>Gibelline,</hi> and that he ſhould dye with the <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellines;</hi> of whom <hi>Caeleſtinus</hi> his Predeceſſor, a man famous as they ſay for Miracles,<note n="n" place="margin">Aſcendiſti ut vulpes, reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabis ut Leo, morieris ut Canis, &amp; it a ſane contigit, Tho. Walſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham in Edu. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> profeſſed that as he entred life a Fox, he ſhould reign like a Lyon, and die like a
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:58390:78"/>dog, which fell out accordingly.</p>
            <p>Why might ſhe not ſit there as well as <hi>Gregory</hi> the 7, commonly known by the name of <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> who ſet the<note n="o" place="margin">Abbas <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pergenſis in Chron. ad an. <hi>1080.</hi>
               </note> Church and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth on fire; who hired a villain to tumble down great ſtones from the Battlements of a Church upon the Emperours head, to ſqueeze him to pieces, whilſt he was at prayers, as Cardinal <hi>Benno</hi> reports, who caſt the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment into the fire, who uſually carryed about him a Conjuring-book; who ſoundly baſted his Predeceſſor <hi>Alexander;</hi> who wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted the Scriptures to cover his lewdneſs:<note n="p" place="margin">Florentinus Vigornierſis in Chron. page <hi>641.</hi> Mat. Paris in Guil. Conqueſt. An. <hi>1086.</hi>
               </note> who at his death con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, that the Devil ſet him on work to provoke God to wrath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the World.</p>
            <p>Why might ſhe not ſit there as well as <hi>John</hi> the 23. (<hi>Onuph. Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendix</hi> 24,) who was fitter for the Camp than for the Church; for
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:58390:78"/>Profaneneſs, than for Piety; as knowing no Faith, no Religion at all; who openly profeſſed that there was no life after this, (—<hi>poſt mortem nulla voluptas</hi>) but that it was with Men as with Beaſts: who, in a word, lived ſo ſcandalouſly, that he was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called the Devil Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate.</p>
            <p>Why might ſhe not ſit there as well as <hi>John</hi> the 12.<note n="q" place="margin">Luitprand. Hiſt. de Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rop. geſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, lib <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>7.8.</hi> &amp; <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> who made Deacons in a Stable, who made a Boy of ten years old a Biſhop; who made the <hi>Lateran</hi> a common Bawdy-houſe; who drank to the Devil; who, when he was at Prayers, invoked <hi>Jupiter</hi> and <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> and other Idolatrous Gods of the Heathens, who at length was ſlain even by the Devil him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, whilſt he was committing Adultery, as I ſaid before. If it cannot be denyed that God hath ſuffer'd theſe and as many as wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:58390:79"/>as any of theſe (except the laſt recited) to ſeat themſelves in St. <hi>Peters</hi> Chair, we need not wonder with<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Part.</hi> 2. <hi>Tit.</hi> 16. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>Sect.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>Antonius</hi> at the ſtory of Pope <hi>Joan,</hi> and ſay, oh the depth of the Wiſdome of God, how incredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble are his judgments! <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now let me ask any Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt this queſtion: how ſhould this tale of <hi>Pope Joan</hi> ariſe if there had not been ſuch a Pope; Was there ever ſuch a Smoak and no fire; ſuch a report, and no Proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility: To this ſome Romaniſts do ſay, that great lyes do always ariſe out of ſome Truth: <hi>omnia inſignia mendacia ab aliqua veritate originem habent,</hi> ſaith <hi>Onuphrius</hi> in his notes on <hi>Platina</hi> in the Life of <hi>Pope Joan,</hi> and ſo did this, confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that <hi>John</hi> the twelfth was a Whore-maſter, and among other of his <hi>Bona Roba</hi>'s, or Wenches that he kept, there was one called <hi>Joan,</hi> who was all in all with him,
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:58390:79"/>and ruled the roaſt. Now the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple perceiving what intereſt ſhe had in, and power over him, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning him, gave her the appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of Pope. Whereupon the Churches enimies took occaſion to ſlander the Church, as though the Church had (indeed) a woman Pope. And this<note n="ſ" place="margin">Loco ſupr<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> citato.</note> 
               <hi>Onuphri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> proves out of <hi>Luitprandus Tici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſis</hi> a Writer of that Age, who affirms, that <hi>John</hi> the 12 had three famous Strapping Whores, of whom the handſomeſt, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the beſt beloved, was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Joan.</hi> In anſwer hereunto, I read in<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>Luitprandus,</hi> in the place cited by <hi>Onuphrius,</hi> that <hi>John</hi> the 12 kept one eminent whore whom he called <hi>Raynera,</hi> whom he made Governour of many Cities, and on whom he beſtowed many Golden Croſſes, and Chalices belonging to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and relates further, that he kept another cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:58390:80"/>
               <hi>Stephana,</hi> and that he debauch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and vitiated marryed wives, widows, and Maidens, who came to viſit the Apoſtolical Churches, and withal writes, that he kept a third called <hi>Anna,</hi> who was a wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and not ſo, but kept her Neece to boot; making the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace <hi>Lateran</hi> no better than a Baw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy-houſe, but he nowhere menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons any <hi>Joan,</hi> on whom that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent and worthy head of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Church <hi>John</hi> the 12 doted. <hi>Onuphrius,</hi> I ſuppoſe, wanting Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacles miſtook <hi>Joanna</hi> for <hi>Anna.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I but ſay ſome, <hi>John</hi> the 9 was made Biſhop of <hi>Bonony,</hi> then of <hi>Ravena,</hi> and at laſt Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> by the means of one <hi>Theodora</hi> a very famous Whore, who in thoſe days, at <hi>Rome</hi> over-ruled all af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs Eccleſiaſtical or Political. Now it being generally obſerved how prevalent this <hi>Theodora</hi> was with this <hi>John,</hi> and howmuch a
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:58390:80"/>ſlave he was to all her Humours and commands, he was concluded to have deſerved rather the name of a woman than a man, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore called him <hi>Joan,</hi> not <hi>John;</hi> and upon this account aroſe the report of a Pope <hi>Joan;</hi> and to back this aſſertion,<note n="u" place="margin">Annal. l. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Aventinus</hi> a <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> is produced; but <hi>Genebrard,</hi> who is a profeſt rigid Papiſt, dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers in opinion; for ſaith he, <hi>Aven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus lib.</hi> 4. <hi>Annal. fabullam eſſe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerit a Theodora nobili ſcorto ortam; ego vero a recentioribus adulatoribus in Romanae ſedis odium;</hi> that is <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventinus</hi> holdeth that this tale aroſe by reaſon of a noble Whore called <hi>Theodora;</hi> but I think ſome later ſycophantiſing Paraſyts of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors, invented this ſtory, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credit the Papal ſeat: I know not but that <hi>Genebrard</hi> may be as au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick as <hi>Aventinus,</hi> ſince he ſpent<note n="x" place="margin">Prafatio Chronog. ad Pontacum.</note> 10 whole years upon his Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle.</p>
            <pb n="154" facs="tcp:58390:81"/>
            <p>Beſides, ſuppoſe we allow that <hi>John</hi> who was firſt Biſhop of <hi>Bono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> then of <hi>Ravenna,</hi> and laſtly of <hi>Rome,</hi> came to thoſe Biſhopricks by the means of <hi>Theodora</hi> a famous Whore; in reſpect whereof, Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>Baronius</hi> queſtions whether he was a Pope or not, and terms him ſometimes<note n="y" place="margin">Annal. ad annum. <hi>912.</hi> num. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Pſeudopontifex,</hi> and <hi>Anti-papa,</hi> a falſe Pope, and Anti-pope,<note n="z" place="margin">Ad annum <hi>928.</hi> num. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> ſometimes <hi>intruſor &amp; detentor injuſtus Apoſtolicae ſedis;</hi> an intruder and an Uſuper of the Apoſtolical chaire; yet I deny that this was <hi>John</hi> the 9, but <hi>John</hi> the 10: <hi>John</hi> the 9 took no indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect courſes to gain the Papacy, but lawfully and honeſtly, and died naturally, as the ſaid<note n="a" place="margin">Annal. Tom. <hi>10.</hi> ad annum <hi>901.</hi> num. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> Cardinal reports: but ſo did not this;<note n="b" place="margin">Frodoard Hiſt. Rhem. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> This confirmed a Child under five years of age in the Arch-Biſhoprick of <hi>Rhemes,</hi> at which fact <hi>Baronius</hi> ſtands amazed, and could not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear ſaying; than this<note n="c" place="margin">Annal. num. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>turpior
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:58390:81"/>nullus cujus ſicut ingreſſus in Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dram Petri infamiſſimus, ita &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itus nefandiſſimus:</hi> there was never a filthier fellow than this. This entred with infamy and dyed fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully: this was ſtifled with a pillow by the procurement of one as fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for Whoredom as <hi>Theodora</hi> who preſerved him.</p>
            <p>Now ſuppoſe he was <hi>John</hi> the ninth; if his looſe carriage with <hi>Theodora</hi> gave occaſion of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of a Woman Pope, why was it not recorded, as hapning in his time, but above forty years before his time; <hi>John</hi> the ninth was conſtituted Pope in the year 901, yet this ſtory is recorded as hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning about the year 854, to this the Romaniſts reply, that this came to paſs by the ſubtlety of the repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, for ſay<note n="d" place="margin">Florimond. cap. <hi>30.</hi> nu. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> they, about the year 800, the Empreſs, who in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ruled all the world, was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Theodora.</hi> Now theſe trifling
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:58390:82"/>Tale-tellers (to uſe their own words) hearing of a Pope <hi>Joan</hi> in <hi>Theodoras</hi> time, chopt it into the time of <hi>Theodora</hi> the Empreſs, who lived about thirty years before <hi>Theodora</hi> the Harlot.</p>
            <p>I do think this rather argues ſimplicity than ſubtlety in the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porters; for <hi>Cui bono,</hi> whether it hapned in the one or the other <hi>Theodoras</hi> time? But it carries no colour of truth with it; for <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dora</hi> the Empreſs never carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſway in <hi>Rome</hi> at all. At <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople</hi> for a while, in the time of her Sons minority, ſhe had great power:<note n="e" place="margin">Baron. an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. Tem. <hi>10.</hi> ad an. <hi>855.</hi>
               </note> but in Pope <hi>Joans</hi> time ſhe was turned out of office or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted of that Power ſhe had aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> nay, ſhe was depoſed of her regency, and thruſt into a Monaſtery where ſhe was deteined till the Expiration of her life.</p>
            <pb n="157" facs="tcp:58390:82"/>
            <p>Now, ſince this fallacy will ſtand them in no ſtead, they imagin this tale, as they call it, aroſe from <hi>John</hi> the 8, for <hi>John</hi> the 8, ſay they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hav'd himſelf not like a man to <hi>Photius</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> but ſheepiſhly, and like a woman; for he received <hi>Photius</hi> into Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, who was excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by his Predeceſſors. <hi>John</hi> the 8, ſuffer'd himſelf to be overcome by half a man, whereupon, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, he was called, not <hi>Papa ſed Papiſſa,</hi> and this they farther on <hi>Baronius,</hi> of which he writes in his Annals; but how juſtly let any judge, ſince he is one of thoſe who affirm that the rumour of the Church of <hi>Conſtantinoples</hi> overſight, in ſuffering a woman to creep in to be Patriarch, occaſioned this tale againſt <hi>Rome,</hi> according to his own words, <hi>quae ita erant fama vulgata de Eccleſia Conſtantinop. converſa in Romana<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Eccleſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſchiſmatibus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="158" facs="tcp:58390:83"/>odio proſequentibas, &amp; calumniis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcindentibus quis non intelligat,</hi> ſaith <hi>Baronius</hi> in his Annals, who is he ſo ignorant, that underſtands not that what was reported of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> the ſame was turned by Schiſmaticks as ſpoken againſt <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With what honeſty can he affirm both, ſince<note n="f" place="margin">Annal. Tom. <hi>10.</hi> ad annum <hi>853,</hi> nu. <hi>66.</hi>
               </note> he acknowledgeth if there had been but ſome flying tale of any ſuch accident at <hi>Rome</hi> in former days, Pope <hi>Leo</hi> ſhould firſt have cleared it before he had charged the Church of <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople</hi> with the like. And was there not ſuch a flying report of a woman Pope before <hi>Leo</hi> the 9 his time, in <hi>Baronius</hi> time? How then did <hi>John</hi> the 8 occaſion ſuch a report who lived 140 years before <hi>Leo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many more objections I could here inſert, and anſwer, but that I think I have produced enough
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:58390:83"/>already to convince any man un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biaſſed, of the reality and the truth of this Story, that there was a Pope <hi>Joan.</hi> But ſuppoſe this Story to be true, what prejudice is this to the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> Yes, very much, for if ſhe was Pope, then it will neceſſarily follow, that the Roman Church once hopt head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs; for the Church according to<note n="g" place="margin">Bellar. lib. <hi>3.</hi> de Eccleſia. cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bellarmin,</hi> is defined to be a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Chriſtian-men profeſſing one Faith, under one head, to wit, the Pope: but ſhe, however ſhe carried the name of Pope, was no Pope:<note n="h" place="margin">Rhem. an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not. in <hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>14.</hi> v. <hi>34.</hi>
               </note> for a Woman is not capable of Holy Orders: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Woman cannot play the Pope; therefore all the time of Pope <hi>Joan,</hi> the Church hopt head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs.</p>
            <p>The Papiſts do acknowledge this for a great inconvenience, that the Church ſhould lack a true Head for the time, but that's not
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:58390:84"/>ſo great a matter cry they: for ſo ſhe doth when any Pope dieth, till another be choſen. If this be granted, what a pittiful caſe is the Church in then? Since Chriſts time above 250 Popes, and by conſequence, then the Church hath been headleſs 250 times, yea and ſometimes between the death of one Pope, and the chooſing of another, there have paſſed many days, many months, and ſome years, as you may read in Hiſtory, and particularly <hi>Bodin,</hi> that after <hi>Faelix,</hi> ſometimes Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> St. <hi>Peters</hi> Chair ſtood empty Ten years. Now, if the Church be headleſs, where lies her underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; what ſhall guide her when ſhe is bereaved of her Head?</p>
            <p>But let us weigh another obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, did not (ſay they) St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> hold this opinion upon ſuppoſition of a like caſe, that the Church of Chriſt ſhould not be prejudiced?
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:58390:84"/>Did not<note n="k" place="margin">Auſtin. Epiſt. <hi>165.</hi> ad literas cujuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam Donatiſt.</note> he, having recited the Popes Names from the time of Chriſt to his days, make this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand? VVhat if any <hi>Judas</hi> or Traytor had entered among theſe, or been choſen by the Errour of Men? and anſwereth preſently, <hi>Non praejudicaret Eccleſiae, &amp; inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centibus Chriſtianis.</hi> According to the body of the Popiſh Doctrine this muſt be denyed: for the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts hold that the Pope is head of the Church, and that it is neceſſary to ſalvation to acknowledg him the head; but ſo did not St. <hi>Auſtin.</hi> The Papiſts hold that in a true Church, one Biſhop muſt lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſucceed another, or all is daſht out; but ſo did not St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin:</hi> for he puts the caſe, that ſome Traytor <hi>ſuprepſiſset,</hi> that is, had come in not orderly into the Biſhop of <hi>Romes</hi> ſeat: and yet reſolves that that was not prejudical to Gods Church. Let the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:58390:85"/>conform himſelf in theſe two points of the Popes head-ſhip and ſucceſſion to St. Auſtins judgment, and, then he may the better ſay in this caſe of Pope <hi>Joan,</hi> that which St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaid in the caſe propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; that ſhe had not prejudiced the Church of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Now if it be true that there was a Pope <hi>Joan,</hi> the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> muſt be diſcarded as no true Church: for thus I argue, that is no true Church which cannot give in plain authentical writing, the lawful, orderly, entire, (without any breach) and ſound ſincere ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of Biſhops: but your Church if <hi>Joan</hi> was Pope, cannot give in plain authentical writing the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, orderly, entire, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For by reaſon of her, <hi>Benedict</hi> the 3 could not orderly ſucceed <hi>Leo</hi> the 4; for ſhe was a bar to his ſucceſſion; by her a breach was made in the rank of Popes; and as ſhe was
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:58390:85"/>a notorious Whore, ſo ſhe was no fool; as ſhe ſhamefully baffled the Doctors with her learning, ſo ſhe outwitted them with her policy, and ſate in that ſeat which properly belong'd to men, to the confuſion of the Romiſh Church and perpetual infamy of her Clergy.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, if it be granted there was ſuch a Pope, then Popiſh Prieſts may well doubt of the lawfulneſs of their Miſſion, and Lay-Papiſts of the ſufficiency of their abſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which the Prieſts give them on auricular confeſſion, and of the truth of the real preſence and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation.<note n="l" place="margin">Tolet. ſumma Caſuum Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiae lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> For unleſs the Popiſh Prieſts be admited by a lawful Biſhop, their Prieſthood is inſignificant and of no effect:<note n="m" place="margin">Concil. Trident Seſſ. <hi>14.</hi> Can. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> unleſs Lay-Papiſts be abſolved by a Lawful Prieſt, their abſolution is nothing worth: and<note n="n" place="margin">Bellar. l. <hi>4.</hi> de Eucha. cap. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> unleſs the words of Conſecration be uttered by a lawful Prieſt, intent upon his
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:58390:86"/>buſineſs, ther follows no ſubſtantial change in the Creatures of Bread and Wine. Now how can the Prieſts ſay they were inducted by lawful Biſhops, or the Lay-man abſolved by lawful Prieſts, or Maſſes ſaid by them, ſeeing we read (as I ſaid before) that <hi>Pope Joan</hi> gave orders, Pope <hi>Joan</hi> made Deacons, Prieſts, Biſhops, and Abbots. For it may be well enough ſuppoſed that the Prieſts of this preſent age are deſcended from thoſe who received orders from her. Her ſucceſſors dealt not with her Shavelings, as Pope <hi>John</hi> the 12 did with <hi>Leo</hi> the 8 his Shavel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.<note n="p" place="margin">Sigibert in Chron. ad an. <hi>963.</hi> Baronius Turrecremata &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>John</hi> the 12 degraded them all, and compelled every one of them to ſubſcribe a Paper, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in was writ <hi>Epiſcopus meus</hi> (mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Leo</hi> the 8) <hi>nihil ſibi habuit, nihil mihi dedit,</hi> he had naught for him ſelf, and gave naught to me: but ſo did not <hi>Benedict</hi> the third with
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:58390:86"/>Pope <hi>Joans.</hi> To what hath been ſaid I know not what any Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt in any probability can reply, unleſs he ſay as Lawyers in the caſe of <hi>Barbarius Philippus, Communis error facit jus;</hi> yet that will not ſerve the turn, for though it may be ſo in matters of the Commonwealth, in matters of the Church it cannot be ſo; for an errour in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing touching the Church, proves often an hereſy in concluſion. In matters of the Church preſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on adds no credit to actions of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil beginning.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
